<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Of death a true description and against it a good preparation: together with a sweet consolation, for the suruiung mourners. By Iames Cole merchant.</title>
            <author>Cole, James.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1629</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 190 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 113 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19123</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5533</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105012</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840742</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840742</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5271</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19123)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5271)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1199:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Of death a true description and against it a good preparation: together with a sweet consolation, for the suruiung mourners. By Iames Cole merchant.</title>
                  <author>Cole, James.</author>
                  <author>Hoste, Dierick.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 207, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By A. M[athewes],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1629.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Editor's dedication signed: Dierick Hoste.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the University of Chicago. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Consolation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Death --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Love poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5271:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5271:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5271:2"/>
            <p>OF DEATH A TRVE DESCRIPTION: And againſt it A good Preparation: Together with A ſweet Conſolation, for the ſuruiuing Mourners. By IAMES COLE Merchant.</p>
            <p>Printed at London by <hi>A. M.</hi> 1629.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5271:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:5271:3"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT Worthy his much reſpected friends, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Iohn Milleward</hi> Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, one of the Captaines of this famous Cittie, Mr. <hi>Iohn Awbrey,</hi> Mr. <hi>Edmond Page,</hi> M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>William Gillie,</hi> Mr <hi>William Middelton,</hi> and Mr <hi>Iohn Bludworth.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>D. H.</hi> Merchant, wiſheth all hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe in ſoule and body in this wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, and ete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll glory and bliſſe in the world to come.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Xcuſe mee I pray, (which am now the hand of my
<pb facs="tcp:5271:4"/>deceaſed friend) that I commend theſe his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Inſtructions, vnto your Patronages and Embracements. The long time of your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, honeſt mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall traffique, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer pious conuerſation, may iuſtly challenge it, both of the Author, and my ſelfe: Yee often haue taken and built your cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit on his word, in your bought Wares, which
<pb facs="tcp:5271:4"/>the effect hath confirmed to your profit. Once more beleeue him, and buy theſe his Meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, on his word, the price is but your acceptance, read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and application. And if thus you will vſe, and trie theſe his laſt Marchandizes, they will prooue vnto you, of infinite worth, and price, for by them you ſhall obtaine that precious Pearle and hidden trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,
<pb facs="tcp:5271:5"/>of which the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell mentions. It was your charitable &amp; Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian loue, that accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied his mortall body to his laſt home, and it was his louing care, here to direct thoſe that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him, and others to the graue, leſt they ſhould too long make their aboade with the Gaderenian, among the tombes. The graue is but a paſſage, not a dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb facs="tcp:5271:5"/>place. It doth but preſerue the pledge of our bodies vntill the day of reſurrection. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe that truly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low deceaſed Chriſtians, follow them not onely vnto the dore of death, and entrance of the graue, but through death vnto life, through the graue vnto heauen. And leſt death, the way to life, ſhould ſeeme too terrible, and rather af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright
<pb facs="tcp:5271:6"/>from the way, then inuite vnto it. This our friend and charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Author ſhewes and proues here, that in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the body, the ſoule, the world, the laſt Iudgement, it properly is not to be feared. And further to embolden the weake faith of a trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling Chriſtian, hee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maskes and vnarmes death, hee ſo deſcribes her, and prepares our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
<pb facs="tcp:5271:6"/>to embrace her, that death is no more death, but victory: no more the obiect of feare, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire. Wherefore hauing thus farre ſet in a word the deſcription, of her deſcription, before you, I dare no longer detaine you from the victory of her: If you pleaſe but to follow either the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, or example of this our louing friend through death vnto life,
<pb facs="tcp:5271:7"/>through the graue vnto heauen. J dare promiſe, that you will attaine my wiſh, all happineſſe here, and eternall glory here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. Jn confidence whereof I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>London <date>this 10. of Iune, 1629.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your well-wiſhing friend, DIERICK HOSTE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:5271:7"/>
            <head>In commendation of the Author and his Booke.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>NOthing more ſure to vs, then once pale death to ſee,</l>
               <l>Why then are we ſo blinde, not once to thinke thereon?</l>
               <l>What more vncertaine then when this our chance may be?</l>
               <l>Why then goe we on ſtill, as if ſhee ſhould touch none?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In ſeaſonable time, this Book<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is come to light,</l>
               <l>To driue out of our hearts, deaths feare and anguiſh ſtill,</l>
               <l>It is a Chriſtian part, t'inſtruct vs in the right</l>
               <l>How we may arme our ſelues againſt that feared ill.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:5271:8"/>
            <lg>
               <l>For though at euery one, grim death ne're leaues to ayme,</l>
               <l>Yet in this Treatiſe ſmall, from her quite taken is,</l>
               <l>Her ſting. Which iuſtly makes, to tremble without blame,</l>
               <l>But to vs that are Chriſts, ſhe brings eternall bliſs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>O worthy Iſraelite,</hi> thou haſt ſpied out full well,</l>
               <l>That this great <hi>Anakim,</hi> cannot hinder at all,</l>
               <l>To winne that <hi>Canaan</hi> of heau'n, and there to dwell;</l>
               <l>For IESVS CHRIST hath wrought, that Giants great downefall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How can we now reward thy loue, O Author kinde?</l>
               <l>Who in thy life time, ſhun'dſt mens praiſe, from laud didſt flie,</l>
               <l>Thy pious, vertuous life, wee'll euer beare in minde,</l>
               <l>Which now the Lord hath crown'd, with bliſſe eternally.</l>
            </lg>
            <bibl>
               <hi>D. H.</hi>
            </bibl>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:5271:8"/>
            <head>Of the zealous Author, his much reſpected Vnkle, and his comfortable Deſcription.</head>
            <l>SHall I reioyce becauſe his Penne doth teach</l>
            <l>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s how die, and heauenly bliſſe to reach?</l>
            <l>Or ſhall I mourne, becauſe to be our guide,</l>
            <l>His worthy ſelfe he hath to vs den<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d</l>
            <l>Longer on earth? His words perſwade beliefe,</l>
            <l>Farther confirmance but augments our griefe.</l>
            <l>His Booke ſuffu'd, that pointing Mercurie,</l>
            <l>He needed not to guid vs, and to die.</l>
            <l>His life wee wanted more, that could vs tell</l>
            <l>That hee that liued godly ſhould die well.</l>
            <l>Yet what it was I dare not well ſet downe,</l>
            <l>For feare his aſhes modeſty ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uld frowne.</l>
            <l>But let them ſpeake that comment on his name,</l>
            <l>A man of pious, learned, vpright fame:</l>
            <l>Whoſe words and deedes did ſo concurre in one</l>
            <l>That what he ſaid, t'was true, t'was ſure, twas done;</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:5271:9"/>
            <l>Whoſe vertuous preſence was ſo pretious deere,</l>
            <l>That moſt did wiſh he ſtill might haue beene heere.</l>
            <l>But loe his liberall charity: If thus</l>
            <l>His company was gratefull vnto vs,</l>
            <l>He ſhewes vs how we may enioy it ſtill,</l>
            <l>And ſtriues our wiſhes happier to fulfill</l>
            <l>Then we conceiue: He cann't deſcend againe:</l>
            <l>We muſt aſcend, and there by him remaine.</l>
            <l>Thus while we enter his ſocietie,</l>
            <l>Ours will be Saints and Angels companie.</l>
            <l>But leſt wee ſhould vnskilfull Pilgrims ſtray,</l>
            <l>Not knowing how to goe, which is the way;</l>
            <l>Leſt that our eyes waxe dim'd by ſinfull ſlime,</l>
            <l>That we perceiu'd not which way he did clime,</l>
            <l>Behold in this good legacie of his</l>
            <l>He ſhewes vs the true way, through death, to bliſſe.</l>
            <l>Leſt we ſhould feare th'aff ighting face of death,</l>
            <l>And quake to heare the fare-well of our breath;</l>
            <l>To his olde Mate, he doth vnmaske the fiend,</l>
            <l>Shewes her ſting forceleſſe, prooues our foe our friend.</l>
            <l>So that we bold m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y gaze her in the face,</l>
            <l>And that we fear'd ſo much with ioy embrace.</l>
            <l>She is no euill thing, but naturall,</l>
            <l>According to Gods will common to all.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>The bodie's but a ſleepe, it feeles no paine,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>The ſoule dies not, but mounts vnto the traine</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Of heauenly Saints. Why ſhould earths vanities</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Detaine vs from theſe happy glorious skies?</hi>
            </l>
            <pb facs="tcp:5271:9"/>
            <l>
               <hi>Or feare of iudgement? by it we receiue</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>A ioy which mortall minde cannot conceiue.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Therefore when ſickneſſe pale doth enter in</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>By Gods command, vſherd by in-bred ſinne,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>That meſſenger of death; thy houſe befit,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Thy body, ſoule, and all to welcome it.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Thy ſelfe ſtriue well to arme, death to vnarme,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>By ſhunning ſinne with faith, and feare no harme.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Repent and pray, and to thy heauenly peace,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>And certaine comfort will thy faith encreaſe.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>So that death ſhall thy ſoule not terrifie,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>But be to thee a wiſhed victorie,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Which brings thee to a ioyfull Paradiſe,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Before the Lambe, aboue the ſtarrie skies.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>There is our Author now; and there doth ſhine</l>
            <l>Like a cleare ſtarre, our once Marchant-diuine.</l>
            <l>There he's in his reward. If we deſire</l>
            <l>To beare a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rt in that celeſtiall quire,</l>
            <l>Let vs theſe his directions embrace,</l>
            <l>And follow thus through death his fore-runne trace.</l>
            <l>Then ſhall our end be happy, for they will</l>
            <l>Direct vs through this dale to <hi>Sions</hi> bill.</l>
            <q>
               <l>Vt terror Mortis tibi ſit victoria, larvam</l>
               <l>Aſpicias intus; Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s fera vita placens.</l>
            </q>
            <bibl>Abr. Buſh. <hi>Art. Mag.</hi>
            </bibl>
            <pb facs="tcp:5271:10"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:5271:10"/>
            <head>A DESCRIPTION <hi>OF DEATH.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O <hi>euery thing there is a ſet time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccle. 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>a time to bee borne, and a time to die,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon.</hi> And betweene the time of birth and of death, there paſſed in the firſt ages ſixe, eight, or perhaps ten hundreth yeares. But ſince the time that mans ſinne drew the deluge ouer the whole world, <hi>Man borne of a woman, hath but a ſhort time,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iob.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 14.1.</note> 
               <hi>Iacob</hi> ſaid, <hi>that his dayes were an hundreth and thirty yeares,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 47.9.</note> 
               <hi>and that hee had not
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:5271:11"/>attained to the dayes of his Fathers.</hi> But our dayes (ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi>) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming after him,<note place="margin">Pſal. 90.10.</note> 
               <hi>are but threeſcore yeares and tenne, and at the higheſt, foureſcore.</hi> Yet not one among foureſcore times foureſcore at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vnto that age.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.18.</note> 
               <hi>Dauids</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued childe neuer ſaw the eight day; yea, the life of ſome is ended, before they bee borne. But how well ſo euer we are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered out of our mothers wombe, yet hauing taken ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping in this world, we ſtill ſayle towards our end. And whether wee be fewe or many dayes by the way, death is our laſt port, vnto it we are all bound, and at it muſt euery one arriue. Now what man doth euer commit himſelfe to Sea, and doth not firſt furniſh himſelfe with ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary prouiſion, againſt all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:5271:11"/>tempeſts? How much the more then ought we to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh our ſelues againſt the ſtormes of death, which euery one of vs muſt certainly looke for? hee that intends but a iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney by land, enquires for the moſt commodious way, And doe wee thinke to performe our iourney, from Heauen to earth without any trouble or forecaſt at all? This is a lamentable careleſneſſe.</p>
            <p>For whoſoeuer doth then firſt goe about to prepare himſelfe to dye well, when he feeles ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vpon him, or ſeeth death before his eyes, is like to a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier that beginneth then to forge his weapons, when hee beholds his enemies on the wall. Wee ought to ſpend the whole courſe of our life on the meditation of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:5271:12"/>death; for hee certainly hath liued well, who hath learned well to dye. Prouident <hi>Ioſeph</hi> gathered in the ſeauen yeares of plenty, that which fed him, and thoſe that were with him, in the ſeauen yeares of famine.<note place="margin">Gen. 41.43.</note> In like manner ought wee in our youth and health to make prouiſion of that Spirituall foode that may cheriſh vs towards our end, when wee may chance to bee weake both in body and in minde.</p>
            <p>Hee that is Lord of life and death, open the eyes of our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, and endue vs with his Holy Spirit, that hee may lighten and conduct our ſoules in and thorow the darkneſſe of death. Hee I ſay, that hath by dying ouercome death, graunt that we may know it throughly,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:5271:12"/>to withſtand it valiantly; and hereafter (as Souldiers vnder his banner) happily vanquiſh it.</p>
            <p>To treate hereof orderly;<note place="margin">The originall of Death.</note> we are firſt to know that God crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not death: Hee created the firſt man immortall in ſoule and body:<note place="margin">Zanch de Var. qual. <hi>4.1.</hi>
               </note> ſo that hee might haue liued eternally, had hee but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued the will of his Creator: Yet neuertheleſſe, hee alſo crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him mortall, ſo that hee might dye, whenſoeuer hee ſhould tranſgreſſe the law of his Creator. This appeares vnto vs by the words, wherein GOD threatneth him on this manner, <hi>In the day that thou eateſt thereof,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 2.17.</note> 
               <hi>thou ſhalt ſurely die,</hi> ſpeaking of the forbidden tree of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. Wherefore, Ieſus the ſonne of <hi>Sirach</hi> ſayes, that <hi>God himſelfe made man from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:5271:13"/>and left him in the hand of his owne counſell.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.14.17.</note> 
               <hi>He ſet before him life and death</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>and which hee liketh ſhall bee giuen him</hi> Now, when <hi>Adam</hi> (through the Ser<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pents ſubtilty) ſlighted this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine warning, hee ſtraightwayes became lyable to death, both in reſpect of his body which was duſt,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>and ſhall returne to duſt againe,</hi> as alſo of his ſoule; <hi>for through this ſinne was hee adiudged to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5.16.</note> And not hee onely, but alſo all his poſterity, <hi>who all died in Adam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.22.</note> as the Apoſtle teacheth. So then this death (as we may ſay) was begot of the deuill, brought into the world by ſinne, borne in <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> the Mid-wife <hi>Eue,</hi> the Nurſe <hi>Adam.</hi> It hath an abominable mother, that mainely doth reſiſt God: It is lamentable of it ſelfe, in reſpect
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:5271:13"/>that it is the fruit of our tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion. It is ignominious, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is vnto vs as a brand of Gods wrath. Yet is it not ſo abominable, as the mother of it, ſinne it ſelfe, becauſe it doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute Gods iuſt iudgement on vs, ſlaying vs three manner of wayes, whence it alſo may bee termed three-fold.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Death three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold.</note> Firſt, it killeth the body in ſeparating the ſame from the ſpirit, which is the life of it, <hi>for the body without the ſpirit is dead,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iames.</hi> This kinde of death is common vnto all men. It aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailes vs, out of our owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or may be inflicted on vs by others. And from this, ſhall all men be freed, at the generall reſurrection.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it ſlayeth the ſoule by with-drawing the ſame from
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:5271:14"/>God her Creator,<note place="margin">Pſal. 36.9.</note> 
               <hi>who is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of life,</hi> and from God her Redeemer,<note place="margin">Pro. 3.22.</note> 
               <hi>who is the life of our ſoule, and the word of life.</hi> This manner of death, is alſo common vnto all thoſe <hi>that walke as yet in Vanity and Blindneſſe of heart.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 1.11.</note> It befalleth vs by meanes of our ſinnes and treſpaſſes.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.17.</note>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.1.</note> And from this in this preſent life, as many are freed,<note place="margin">Col. 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>as Chriſt hath quickned together with him, and hath forgiuen them all their treſpaſſes,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh. And this it is, that Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> termes the firſt reſurrection.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it kills ſoule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy both together by excluding them both from the bliſſe of eternall life. And of this kinde of death, Chriſt ſaith, <hi>If a man keepe my ſaying,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 8.31.</note> 
               <hi>hee ſhall neuer ſee death.</hi> Whereby the contrary
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:5271:14"/>is proued, to wit, that vnto them that do reiect the word of God, this death ſhall befall, and will come vpon them by the iuſt ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, which at the laſt day God ſhall pronounce againſt them. Nor ſhall any of thoſe, whom it befalleth, euer be releaſed, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this, nor in the world to come. Theſe three ſorts of dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, are all comprehended by Chriſt in a ſpeech of his, where he ſaith, <hi>Feare not them which kill the body,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 10.28.</note> 
               <hi>but are not able to kill the ſoule, but feare him rather who is able to deſtroy both ſoule and body in hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Death two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold.</note> This hell, Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> in his <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelation,</hi> at the laſt ſees throwne into a lake of fire,<note place="margin">Reu. 20.15.</note> and calls it the ſecond death. And ſo he makes death but two-fold: one cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall in this world, the other
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:5271:15"/>ſpirituall in the other world, whoſe diuiſion we alſo willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly embrace.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The death of the body.</note> That death then whereof we meane to treate, is the firſt or corporall death, to wit, that which doth ſeparate the ſoule from the body, and is euery where vſually knowne by the name of death. For whatſoeuer we ſpeake or reade of dying, as well in the diuine bookes of the Bible, as in humane Writers, it is for the moſt part to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of this kinde of death. This death is alſo chiefly feared of men, and cauſeth them to bee troubled, maketh them faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted, and vnconſtant, and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on occaſion of any euill rumour fearefull. Yea, that wiſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turaliſt <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> was of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eth.</hi> 3.</note> that of all things there is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:5271:15"/>nothing more terrible then death.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of them that doe not feare death.</note> If then this death be the moſt terrible thing in the world, how happy is he that is releaſed from the feare of it? Yea verily, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with can the world make him to tremble, that contemnes the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vttermoſt of her power? If hee liue in a Citie infected with the plague, if hee dwell in a Country flaming with warre, if he trauell in danger of theeues, or if a tempeſt at ſea ouertake him, his ſpirits are not daunted, nor his ſenſes benum'd. Hee hath the more reſt, and yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the more danger. Yea, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the leſſe, becauſe a man that is affrighted by his very frights, may bring ſome ſickneſſe vpon himſelfe, and ſo conſequently death. But ſuch a reſolute man
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:5271:16"/>is certaine, that come the worſt, nothing can be exacted of him, beyond his life, which hee ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; and is willing to ſurrender, where, and when it ſhall pleaſe God. If hee be called of God to a Souldier condition, he figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth boldly for the defence of his Country. Yea certainely, hee that oft-times through a cowardly feare would looſe the field, by this his couragious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution putteth his enemie to flight. Thus is euen our life ſometimes lengthened by this willingneſſe to dye. Beſides, if ſuch a one liue by enuious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, or vnder tyrannizing Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, he ſhall not neede to flatter, nor to faine againſt his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. He is not aſtoniſht, though they threaten to ſlay his body: for hee knowes that it muſt dye
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:5271:16"/>whether they threaten him or no. Yea, if they put him to death, he knowes that they euen then bereaue themſelues of power to torment him any far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And is not this a great li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and worthy to be ſought after? whereas on the contrary, how miſerable is that man, that is continually encumbred with feare, and that not for ſome thing, that hee may hope or chance to eſcape, but for that which vndoubtedly may, yea muſt ſometime befall him. Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch a one walkes throughout the courſe of his life in a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall flight, farre worſe then death it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The diuiſion of the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe.</note> Well then, for the better ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming of this feare, wee will aſſay for to vnmaske death, and diſrobe it of all terrible appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rition,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:5271:17"/>that ſo wee may behold it naked, and in his owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And firſt wee ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour by foure naturall reaſons, and then by foure other obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations, to demonſtrate that it hath nothing in it ſelfe that ſhould be terrible vnto vs. And ſecondly, proceeding, we hope, likewiſe in a foure-fold diſcourſe manifeſtly to ſhew, that to thoſe that know how to arme themſelues againſt it, death is altogether profitable, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently worthy to bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired.</p>
            <p>This death then,<note place="margin">1 Reaſon.</note> though it be one of the twinnes which to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether <hi>by ſin entred into the world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Death is not bad.</note>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5.12.</note> yet doth it in no manner of wayes reſemble in iniquity the ſpirituall death its ſiſter. For though this death doe vtterly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:5271:17"/>ſlay the body, and the other doth not kill the ſoule, but caſts it into a miſerable life, yet is it better to dye by the firſt, then to liue in the ſecond. Yea, by meanes of this obtaine wee this benefit and profit, that at the laſt it doth free vs from this toyle-ſome life, to which God (ſince the fall of man) hath heere on earth condemned all mankinde. In the which, were it not that this death preuenteth it, wee ſhould continually remaine. For this cauſe then, as alſo for that God doth ſend it, as well to his children, whom he loueth, as to his enemies, whom he hateth, it cannot in its owne nature be euill. Howbeit, God doth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſly addreſſe it vnto vs. For the wicked <hi>hee conſumes in his wrath,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 45.19.</note> 
               <hi>as vnworthy of this temporall
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:5271:18"/>life:</hi> But the godly <hi>hee takes away in his mercy and peace:</hi> as eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them worthy of a better life.<note place="margin">2 Reg. 22.20.</note> And thus is death vnto the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates a paſſage vnto eternall miſery, but to the Righteous, vnto eternall life.<note place="margin">Ioh. 5.24.</note> Euen as a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter thruſteth his diſobedient ſeruant out of dores to deliuer him vnto the Iaylor, and lets forth his obedient, to ſet him at liberty for euer. Yet is it one, and the ſame doore that both paſſe thorow. Who then will terme this doore, or this death euill? If death in it ſelfe be not euill, then from it directly no euill can bee expected. Let this then be the firſt reaſon, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we neede not feare death.</p>
            <p>But ſome may heere object, that it is the occaſion of this euill, that wee by meanes of it,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:5271:18"/>looſe this temporall life, which is ſweet to euery one. But in ſooth for vs to pay that we owe, may not bee termed any loſſe vnto vs. And who knoweth not the condition of this life? All things which by birth haue a beginning, haue an end by death. Whoſoeuer therefore feareth the end, muſt not deſire the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning. Our life is like vnto a candle, if wee deſire it to giue light in lightning, it muſt burne, and burning, draw, and come to an end. If the Sunne would not deſcend, it muſt not aſcend. For the ſame courſe that cauſeth it to aſcend, cauſeth it to deſcend, euen ſo doth this life conduct vs to death. And who then can ſay this life is good, and death euill? Certainly whatſoeuer is ſpoken againſt death, oppoſes
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:5271:19"/>life, which is the cauſe of death. <hi>Epictetus</hi> his ſaying is good, <hi>Death</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>is not frightfull, but the feare of death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ar. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>and to dye is not ill, but to dye ſhamefully.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence <hi>Socrates,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Reaſon. Death Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</note> when tydings was brought vnto him, that the Gouernours of <hi>Athens</hi> had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned him to dye: <hi>And ſo hath Nature them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A poph, Eraſ. 4.</note> ſaid hee, without any farther alteration. He knew well that it was no leſſe naturall to dye, then to liue. And this ſhall be the ſecond reaſon wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore death is not to be feared. <hi>All fleſh</hi> (we read in <hi>Eccleſiaſticus</hi>) <hi>waxeth old as a garment,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 14.18.</note> 
               <hi>for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree from the beginning is, thou ſhalt dye the death. As of the greene leaues, vpon a thicke tree, ſome fall, and ſome growe, ſo is the generation of fleſh and blood. One commeth to an end, and another is borne. Euery
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:5271:19"/>worke rotteth, and conſumeth away.</hi> Yea, to what end doth the corne ſpring vp into eares, but to bee reaped? And doth not euery lowe ebbe make way to a new flood? Doth not euery day by declining, giue time vnto the approaching night? The ſame courſe of enterchange, is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe among men, the precedent giues place vnto the future. The Elements and all things compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of them, are ſubiect vnto mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; yea, <hi>the heauens them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſhall be diſſolued and renewed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet 3.12.</note> How then can a mortall body for euer remaine? <hi>Being but a houſe of clay, that is ſoone broke downe. It comes vp like a flower, and is ſoone cut downe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 14.2.</note> Yea what is the life of this body?<note place="margin">1 Chron 29.15.</note> 
               <hi>A ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, a winde,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 7 7.</note> 
               <hi>a vapour that appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth for a little,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>and then vaniſheth
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:5271:20"/>away,</hi> ſaith holy writ. As an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe once being ſhot, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally flye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h to the place where it muſt be fixed: So man once be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing borne, paſſeth without inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion vnto that end where hee muſt reſt.</p>
            <p>Yea we our ſelues (if we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue it) are continually dying from the firſt day of our birth. Our childhood dyed in vs when we became youthes. Our youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full age when wee grew to bee men. The day preſent deſtroyeth the day paſt, and euery preſent houre, yea moment, ſlayes that that is newly paſt: yet doth not the abſence of the time paſt hurt vs, nor doe we bewaile it, though euen now we want time. Much leſſe then (if death at this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſhould hurry vs away.) Should the want of the preſent
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:5271:20"/>time then procure any loſſe to vs, when as the time of this world in no wiſe further can auaile vs. So that there is not any naturall reaſon why death ſhould affright vs. No reaſon I ſay, which is hence alſo appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, in that the antienter ſort, doe oftentimes more abhorre death then the younger, where as reaſon rather requireth the contrary. This deſire therefore of delay in olde men, ſprings onely out of an habituated lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of theſe two friends, ſoule and body; the coniunction of the which, the longer it laſteth, the cloſer is their amity knit toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to wit, ſo long till they be ſufficiently enformed, that their ſeparation can be no loſſe vnto them, and no longer. Yea na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it ſelfe, directs all things to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:5271:21"/>their end. The faireſt bloſomes ſhee cauſeth freely to ſhed their pleaſant leaues, that the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cods may finde place. Theſe doth ſhe alſo cauſe to ſhrinke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and ſplit, that the ſeede may fall out of them, into the lap of the earth where it ought to be. Wee our ſelues alſo haue a continuall naturall longing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our end, and wiſh (though wee doe not obſerue it) that our dayes might haſten their courſe. What is it elſe when as children long to be great? thoſe of middle growth to be married? the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to ſee their children come to age? yet is it certaine, that how much the more we obtaine of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe our wiſhes, we approach the neerer to our end, and yet we wiſh for it. Yea farther, who knowes not that fire at the laſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:5271:21"/>ſhall bring this world to an end; yet is it ſo farre from terrifying vs, that in ſigne of publique and generall ioy, we are accuſtomed to kindle extraordinary great bonfires.</p>
            <p>We haue alſo farre more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, to ſee mens deceaſe then their birth. No body r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nnes forth for pleaſure, to ſee a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in labour: you will ſay, the reaſon is, becauſe there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing therein but calamity and paine. And what is there elſe, where two fighting, hurt one the other, and yet who deſires not to be a ſpectator? Or if any by the Magiſtrates command, muſt ſuffer a painefull dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h, what running is there to ſee it? And who among vs would not take great delight (if he could but ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely behold it out of a win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:5271:22"/>to ſee ſome-where a bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell fought in the field? The Romane Emperors who in fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, knew well enough how to entice the people, and to get their fauour, did on feaſtiuall dayes preſent them with cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine hundred paires of Fencers, which freely ſported, till that commonly, one of each couple couered his ſtanding with his dead body. And on this ſport (for ſo they called it) did the people ſit gazing whole dayes, without ſhowe of wearineſſe. Yea, it ſeemes that the ſame was firſt brought in by the Iſraelites, when <hi>Abner</hi> and <hi>Ioah</hi> cauſed their Souldiers to ſport together on this wiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 2.14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Behold then how farre man euen beyond all decencie, taketh pleaſure in ſeeing the death of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:5271:22"/>others, when hee ſuffereth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be led, by his naturall inclination. So that to dye, is not onely naturall, but it ſeemes there is alſo a ſecret deſire to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Tragedy of it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">3 <hi>Reaſon. Death vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l.</hi>
               </note> to whom can any thing ſeeme terrible, that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents it ſelfe dayly before his eyes? What is more common among vs, then Chriſtnings and Burialls? Haue euer any beene knowne of all that haue beene borne, not to haue dyed? Old, young, rich, poore, honeſt, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt, all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>read that path.<note place="margin">Gen. 4.8.</note> 
               <hi>Abel</hi> (it may bee) was ſlaine in his youth,<note place="margin">Gen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.27.</note> and <hi>Methuſalah</hi> liued wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigh a thouſand yeares, yet hee died alſo.<note place="margin">Exod. 14.8.</note> The impious <hi>Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> were drowned in the red ſea: Gods people periſhed in the wildernes. Poore <hi>Lazarus</hi> died,<note place="margin">Luk. 16.22.</note>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:5271:23"/>the rich man died alſo, ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Luke.</hi> Yea, that mighty <hi>Ahaſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſt. 1.1.</note> who raigned ouer a hundred and ſeauen and twenty Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that great <hi>Alexander,</hi> the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> who conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the whole world, haue all bin conquered by this death.</p>
            <p>All things that are created, as fire, ayre, water, earth, and all things compounded and ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of them, are able to inflict death on vs. <hi>Anacreon</hi> the Poet, was choaked with a grape ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell, Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> the fourth with a flye. Yea, in our ſelues doth not the leaſt diſturbance of our blood, oft end our liues? Anger, heat, colde, a fright, doe the ſame. I ſpare to ſpeake of a plague, which in the ſpace of ſeauen or eight moneths, hath deuoured in one Citie of <hi>London,</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:5271:23"/>eight and thirty thouſand. Or a ſiedge, which without and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Towne of <hi>O oſlend,</hi> hath ſwept away more then a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand men, in leſſe then three yeares. This we ſee, and this we heare dayly, and ſuch like accidents fill the greater part of leaues in all manner of Chronicles, and this will bee common as long as men ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit the world. Haue we not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> great reaſon ſo to accuſtome our ſelues to theſe common chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that we may not be affrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by them? But what doe I number men, we ſee whole Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties deſtroyed. That mighty Citie of <hi>Troy</hi> now giueth the Plow-man leaue to f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rrowe her. Holy <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> can hardly ſhew one ſtone on the other. The Maieſtie of <hi>Rome</hi> muſt now be
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:5271:24"/>gueſſed out of her Ruines.<note place="margin">Gen. 19.23.</note> Yea, a fire kindled in <hi>Canaan,</hi> and burnt foure Cities together, with all the Inhabitants.<note place="margin">Ann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>14<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1.</hi>
               </note> A flood drowned in <hi>Holland</hi> three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore and twelue Villages, with whole houſholds inhabi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing the ſame. And ſhall we then for our ſelues bee ſo grieued, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as each of vs is but one ſilly man?</p>
            <p>And yet aboue all,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>4</hi> Reaſon. Death is Gods will.</note> we haue no reaſon to diſturbe our ſelues, in that which is Gods will and pleaſure. Hee hath ſet a law to all his creatures, which they muſt obay.<note place="margin">Pſal. 148.6.</note> Immediatly after the Creation, he ſpake to man, and ſaid, <hi>Earth thou art, and to earth thou ſhalt returne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.9.</note> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore well ſaith <hi>Salomon, All liuing know that they ſhall dye.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 9.5.</note> When God onely ſaith, <hi>Returne yee chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:5271:24"/>of men:</hi> (ſingeth Moſes) <hi>they are carried away as with a flood,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 90.3.5.</note> 
               <hi>as a ſleepe, and as graſſe that is wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Feare not death</hi> (ſaith the ſonne of <hi>Sirach) for remember that this is the ſentence of the Lord ouer all fleſh;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 41.5.</note> 
               <hi>of them that goe before thee, and of them that come after. And why art thou againſt the pleaſure of the moſt high?</hi> Let it ſuffice vs to know, that it is Gods comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, and that he is alwayes entirely good,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.22.</note> and <hi>that obedience to him is better then Sacrifice.</hi> This is the fourth reaſon, why wee ought not to ſhunne death. Eſpecially becauſe though wee neuer ſo much ſhunne it, yet can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not we eſcape it: but muſt ſome time or other (will we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill wee) fall into its clawes. If there be then a neceſſity, what folly is it,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:5271:25"/>to wraſtle againſt God and his ordinance? It muſt needes bee eaſier quietly to walke towards our end, then to ſuffer our ſelues to bee dragged to it by force? And although we ſee the yeares of antient folkes ſometimes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed, and of the younger ſort ſhortned, or by misfortune (as it may ſeeme) cut off; yet muſt we not therefore wrangle with our Creator about it, as if it were contrary to reaſon and nature. But ſay with Chriſt, when hee thanked his father, that hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed to children, that which he kept ſecret from the wiſe and prudent (which ſeemes both to oppoſe nature and humane rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) <hi>Euen ſo Father, becauſe it ſeemed good in thy ſight.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 10.21.</note> That then which is pleaſing vnto him, who is onely wiſe, and good,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:5271:25"/>and our father alſo muſt needes ſeeme good vnto vs.</p>
            <p>He that hath brought vs into this world,<note place="margin">Selfe murther is vnlawfull.</note> not when it ſeemed good vnto us, but when it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him, hath alſo good reaſon to take vs from hence, when it ſhall be ſo pleaſing vnto him. We are all his creatures, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long vnto him, and euery one from him poſſeſſeth his body, as a needfull and pretious pledge of his loue, committed on truſt vnto him for a while. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we muſt alwayes be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to reſtore the ſame, when the owner ſhall pleaſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand it, yet in the meane while ought we not either careleſly to looſe, or vnthankfully to caſt away this creature of God. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Stoical Philoſophers doe terme a mans killing of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:5271:26"/>the opening of a doore, through which euery one may freely out-runne the miſeries of this life.<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> Yet did <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> better conſider this matter, who ſhewes that the murthering of a mans ſelfe to eſchew any calamity or ſorrow, doth not argue any va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, but cowardiſe rather. If God by many trialls here, will haue vs trained to fortitude; let vs then not reſemble peeuiſh children, who as ſoone as they are but chidden in their firſt Schoole, runne preſently whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning out of dores. Wee muſt ſhew our ſelues men, and as va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant Souldiers ſtand on our guard, in this world againſt all dangers. As alſo continue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in cold, heat, hunger, thirſt as long as it ſhall pleaſe our Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall to place vs there. <hi>None of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:5271:26"/>vs</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>liueth to himſelfe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 14.7.</note> 
               <hi>therefore whether wee liue or dye, we are the Lords.</hi> If all of vs then are the Lords, it is a point of great iniuſtice for any of vs, according to our owne will, to kill himſelfe. Which ſinne is therefore iuſtly deemed the more damnable, for that the man that murdereth himſelfe, after the committing of the ſin, hath not any time of repentance. It is our duty therefore wholy to referre the length of our life, and did meanes of our death, to the will of God, that ſo in both wee may alwayes with a good conſcience ſay vnto him,<note place="margin">Math. 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>Our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, thy will be done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet many doe not ſhunne death in reſpect of dying, but in reſpect of the condition where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto death bringeth them. Let
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:5271:27"/>vs likewiſe therefore conſider this their future eſtate foure manner of wayes, and ponder each of them ſeuerally.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Obſeruation concerning the body.</note> Firſt, ſome feare the future miſery of their body, when it ſhal be ſeparated from the ſoule. We muſt to this purpoſe vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that the dead in holy Writ, are ſometimes ſaid to ſleepe, and ſometimes to reſt. The one ſeemes to be in reſpect of the body, the other of the ſoule. <hi>Iob</hi> ioyneth them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he wiſheth that his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wombe had bin his tombe, <hi>For now ſhould I</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>haue luine ſtill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 3.13.</note> 
               <hi>and bene quiet, I ſhould haue ſlept, then ſhould I haue beene at reſt</hi> And very fitly is the death of the body compared to ſleepe, for euen as man, at euery finiſhing of the Sunnes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:5271:27"/>is ſubiect to this ſhort ſleepe, euen ſo, when his life hath compaſſed his courſe, the long ſleepe of death ſcaſes on him. And as our bodies per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue no vnquietneſſe in the day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſleepe, in like manner ſhall they feele none, in this long and laſt ſleepe. Hence <hi>Cato</hi> ſaid ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well,<note place="margin">Diſt. Cat.</note> that <hi>ſleepe is the image of death.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoph. Eraſ.</note> 
               <hi>Diogenes</hi> learned of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> to call ſleepe and death bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. If then they bee like the one to the other, wee haue no reaſon to ſhunne the one more then the other. And whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer vnwillingly doth forgoe this body may well bee reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled vnto little children, that are very loath to be vndreſt, that they might bee had to bed by times; but being eaſily laide downe, ſoone fall into a ſweet
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:5271:28"/>ſleepe. If ſleepe then be ſweet to the body, while wee ſleepe, and if a man ſle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ping counts no time, nor tells any houres, but thoſe wherein hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit himſelfe to ſleepe, and thoſe wherein her doth awake, what neede he to care how much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n he ſpend in ſleeping, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they he ſhall ſleepe ſeauen houres in his b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, or ſeauen ages in his graue? And whileſt hee thus counes no time, there remaines for him betweene death and ſleepe no difference at all Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then ſhould he abhorre the one more then the other.</p>
            <p>Now conc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rning the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our body, it is an old ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>the corruption of one thing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ariſtotle.</note> 
               <hi>is the generation of another.</hi> Our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is but changed againe into the ſame elements, whereof it
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:5271:28"/>was at firſt created by GOD, when by him a liuing breath was blowne into it. Which liuing ſoule keepes by force (as it were) theſe elements together. But when the ſame by m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anes of the departure of the ſoule, haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obteined their former freedome, then our body returnes to duſt <hi>whence it was taken,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.19.</note> according to Gods word and ordinance. So that whatſoeuer in our compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition we likewiſe had borrowed from the water, ayre, and fire, returnes each to his owne ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, where it is well at reſt, and at home.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</note> But at the laſt day ſhall God cauſe the elements to ſurrender again the ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ter of our bodies, and then <hi>as many as lye in the earth and ſleepe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 12.6.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall awake</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>not onely thoſe that b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:5271:29"/>predeſtinated to eternall life, but euen thoſe alſo which are ordained to eternall ſhame.</hi> And although wee cannot comprehend, how God ſhall finde, diſtinguiſh, and reforme our bodies, yet neede wee not to doubt of his word. Wee ſee dayly before our eyes, many things come to paſſe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible, before they are expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto vs. Would it not ſeeme vnpoſſible to any of vs, to finde a man in a wood, or way, where no body euer had ſeene him walking. Yet put but on a Beagle, or Blood-hound, and he by the ſent onely will follow, and finde his Maſter. Againe, ſhew the Copies of a hundred ſchoole boyes, vnto al the wiſeſt Philoſophers in the world, it will bee vnpoſſible for them to diſtinguiſh them. Shewe them
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:5271:29"/>but vnto their Schoole-Maſter, hee at the firſt ſight will know euery ones proper hand. In like manner, let a golden bowle be caſt amongſt a hundred pound of melting braſſe, and (as it will be) equally diſperced and mingled with the ſame, will it not ſeeme vn o vs (that haue no inſight in that Art) vnpoſſible to recouer the Cup againe out of the whole maſſe. Giue it but an Alchy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt, he will ſoone extract your gold; giue that then to the Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith, and you ſhall haue your Cup new caſt, as it was before. If ſo be then that a skilfull man, yea a beaſt can bring things o paſſe in this world, which ſeeme vnpoſſible, to the greater and wiſer ſort of men, yea if wee our ſelues can transforme the duſt of the earth, (ſand and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:5271:30"/>aſhes) into a goodly tranſparent glaſſie body. Wee muſt needes expect more from God, <hi>with whom all things are poſsible.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 19.26.</note> Hee that hath created the earth of nothing, and vs, of the earth, <hi>who meeteth out heauen</hi> (as <hi>Eſay</hi> ſpeaketh) <hi>with his ſpanne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 40.12.</note> within which our bodies remaine, (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be in the earth, in the water, or in the entrayles of beaſts) will eaſily finde, know, and re-eſtabliſh all that which he once made, and yet containes in the palme of his hand. Let vs then freely be confident, <hi>that the houre ſhall come,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 5.29.</note> 
               <hi>in the which all that are in the graues, ſhall come forth vnto the reſurrection.</hi> And as death is termed a ſleepe, ſo is the reſurrection, by the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named Prophet,<note place="margin">Dan. 12.2.</note> fitly called an awaking. Yet this reſurrection
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:5271:30"/>will farre ſurpaſſe our dayly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waking out of ſleepe: for now we awake with a body that falls a ſleepe againe: but hereafter we ſhall riſe with a body that neuer can dye any more; for then (ſayes S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>the dead ſhall bee raiſed incorruptible.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.51.</note> So that wee may obſerue, that our bodies doe profit by death: For firſt, wee obtaine a long laſting eaſe; and ſecondly an euerlaſting life. Whence it followeth, that in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of our bodies, wee haue no cauſe at all to ſhunne death.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, concerning the ſoule.</note> Secondly, ſome feare that ſome damage may befall their ſoule by death, which is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt reaſon. The ſoule is not compoſed of ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that is ſubiect vnto the power of death. She is as a liuing ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, by God breathed into vs.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:5271:31"/>And as the brea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h which men blowe out, though it be no eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall part of their lungs or mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; yet notwithſtanding, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth a ſauour of that breaſt that it came f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om: Euen ſo doth our ſoule retaine that, from the image of him, who infuſed it in the body, that it is thereby be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an immortall ſpirit.</p>
            <p>For of the immortality of it neuer was there doubt made by any liuing, vnleſſe by fooles. By them (ſayes the booke of <hi>Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi>) <hi>the ſoules ſeeme to dye,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Wiſd. 3 2 4.</note> 
               <hi>and their departure is taken for miſerie, but their hope it full of immo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tality.</hi> Yea, the very ſoules of the vn beleeuers, are not ſubiect to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, as is manifeſted vnto vs, by the ſoule of the rich man in the Goſpell.<note place="margin">Luke 16.23.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Eccl 12.7.</note> 
               <hi>This body</hi> (ſayes <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi>) <hi>ſhall returne to the earth as it
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:5271:31"/>was, and the ſpirit ſhall returne to God, who gaue it,</hi> to receiue his ſentence either of reward or of puniſhment: For otherwiſe, if the reaſonable ſoule periſhed with the body, then ſhould the moſt godly men (who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly muſt refraine the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of this world, and ſuffer for Gods cauſe contempt at the hand of Reprobates) of all men become the moſt miſerable.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.19.</note> Which could neither agree with Gods Mercy toward the good, nor with his Iuſtice to the bad. The ſoule therefore is to expect hereafter a day of account, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in oppreſſors ſhal be reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>penced with tribulation,<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>and to them that are troubled, ſhall be a refreſhing and reſt.</hi> For indeede the ſoule is the principall part of man,<note place="margin">Deut. 10.12.</note> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as well by <hi>Moſes</hi> in the old
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:5271:32"/>Teſtament,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.20.</note> as by <hi>Peter</hi> in the new, it is taken for the whole man.</p>
            <p>But being ſeperated from this body, will it be able to doe any thing? This wee may in ſome ſort conceiue in this life.<note place="margin">The ſoules ſelfe-conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> For when a mans ſpirit is buſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed in its owne worke, that is, in ſome kinde of meditation, wee may preſently perceiue, that the leſſe the bodily members, yea his fiue ſenſes are occupied, the more earneſter hee withdrawes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to his cogitations. Yea oft he will ſhut his very eyes, that the receiuing of their obiects may not diſturbe him. We read that <hi>Archimedes</hi> his minde was ſo buſied about humane Art,<note place="margin">Val. Max. <hi>8.7.</hi>
               </note> that the very Citie of <hi>Siraci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſa,</hi> where he then abode, was taken, and he himſelfe by the Enemie
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:5271:32"/>ſurpriſed, before hee perceiued the leaſt rumour thereof. And S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul,</hi> when the heauenly viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were reuealed vnto him, hee was ſo farre from needing his bodily members thereunto,<note place="margin">2 Cor 12.2.</note> 
               <hi>that he himſelfe knew not whether he was in the body, or out of the body.</hi> And long time before this, when God would teach <hi>Iacob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 18.10.</note> 
               <hi>Abime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lech, Salomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 20.2.</note> 
               <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and others,<note place="margin">1 Reg 3.5.</note> ſome matters of great moment,<note place="margin">Math. 2.13.</note> did he not firſt let their bodies fall a ſleepe? Hee knew well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, that thine beſt helpe would but haue beene a hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to ſpirituall matters. Doth not this ſhew vnto vs, that the body is but to the ſoule as a clogge tied to the legge. <hi>Seneca</hi> hath well obſerued, how tedious this fleſh is to our ſoule.<note place="margin">Sen.</note> 
               <hi>Now</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>doth the belly ake, then
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:5271:33"/>the ſtomacke, then the throat. Now to there too much blood, anon, too little; And the ſoule is in this body, not as at home in her owne houſe, but as a trauailer in an Inne.</hi> The ſoule then is created to a higher de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, to wit, to liue at eaſe on high in her owne proper dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling place.</p>
            <p>Wherefore <hi>Maximus Tyrius</hi> ſaith very well,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Serm.</hi> 23.</note> 
               <hi>That which men call death, is the beginning of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, and the birth of a future life: To wit, when their bodies at their appointed time fall away, and the ſoules aſcend to their proper place, and to their proper life:</hi> So that this body is to the ſoule, as the egge-ſhell is to the bird, it muſt breake through it before it can flye into the open ayre. Yea <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> the great Monarch, could ſay, that he alwayes beleeued,<note place="margin">Cic. deſen.</note> 
               <hi>That
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:5271:33"/>the ſoule being freed from the body, then became both purt and wiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And although we ſeeme vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to for ſake this body, yet that muſt not breed any ill ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in vs. At our birth, wee ſeemed likewiſe loath to re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>one out of our mothers wombe, where we were weld and warme. Yet now being borne, and vſing all our members in the ſpations world, who of vs would be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to creepe into his mothers wombe againe? In like in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, the ſoule once being ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d out of the cumberſome priſon of the body, will not deſire to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to the ſame againe. For God hath ſo appointed three dwelling places for euery one of vs, that a man by the two firſt, may in ſome ſort conceiue the third. For as, while he is in his
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:5271:34"/>mothers wombe, hee hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing neere ſo much ſtrength, comelineſſe, pleaſure, and time there to remaine, as after his birth, he enioyeth on the face of the earth; ſo cannot he obtaine or enioy that here on earth, that may in any wiſe be compared ſon glory, bliſſe, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, to that which hee ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy, when (borne againe out of his owne body) his ſoule ſhall be fetled on high in the heauens.</p>
            <p>That which the moſt ancient Philoſopher <hi>Hermes Triſmegiſtus</hi> well conceiued,<note place="margin">Fr. Patr. Triſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg.</note> who dying, could ſpeake thus: <hi>As yet haue I liued here; as a ſtranger, and one ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, now I returne againe in health, to my owne Country: And when I preſently (being releaſed from theſe fleſhie bonds) ſhall depart from you; take heede you doe not mourne, as if
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:5271:34"/>I were dead: for I returne to the beſt and happieſt Citie, whither all Citizens ſhall come by the meanes of death. God is there alone the higheſt Prince, who will fill his Citizens with an infinite delight; In reſpect whereof, this, that moſt account life, may rather be called death then life.</hi> If a Heathen could ſpeake thus, all Chriſtians certainly muſt needes (be voide of vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,) and euen dead while they liue, that call in queſtion the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture life of the ſoule.</p>
            <p>Yea, this happy eſtate of the ſoule, did ſo immeaſurably poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe, and ſtrangely tranſport <hi>Cleombrotus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cicer. Tuſe. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> after that hee had read ſomewhat concerning the ſame in <hi>Plato,</hi> that to enioy the ſame, as ſoone as poſſible might be, he caſt himſelfe headlong in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Sea. But zeale here con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:5271:35"/>wiſedome, and by miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſing, good things brought forth bad effects. Howbeit, by this example, well may wee ſhame thoſe, that without reaſon, feare exceedingly the day of death; whereas the day of our birth, is but the beginning of a tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall life; but our dying day, is the beginning of an euerlaſting life: ſo that in reſpect of the ſoule, death ought not to ſeeme terrible vnto vs.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. Obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on concerning carthly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures.</note> Some alſo ſhunne death, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhee bereaues vs of all our earthly pleaſures. They are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to part with their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, riches, delights, their faithfull wife, and deare friends, as fearing that the want of them will be greeuous vnto them. But let vs weigh this alſo in the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of reaſon.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:5271:35"/>
            <p>Whoſoeuer doth ſo eſteeme earthly pleaſures, (which <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> proclaimed to be <hi>vanity of vanities</hi>) that hee would rather chuſe to ſtay here,<note place="margin">Eccl. 1.1.</note> and liue in the ſame, then remoue to enioy the heauenly, may well be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to one, who, becauſe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times hee dreameth of pleaſant things, would rather ſleepe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, then awake and enioy reall pleaſures. For it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that as farre as the reall pleaſures of this life, excell thoſe that appeare vnto vs in our dreames; ſo much are the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall future ioyes to bee prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, before the temporall and preſent.</p>
            <p>The wiſeſt Aſtronomers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade vs,<note place="margin">Som. Scip.</note> that if from the higheſt heauen, wee ſhould behold the Globe of the earth; it would
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:5271:36"/>ſeeme no greater vnto vs, then a ſtarre now doth, and we ſhould eſteeme it, but as a point. And ſhall we in this point, yea in the very leaſt corner of this point, to wit, that which wee inhabite, take ſuch pleaſure, and bee ſo fond of it, that for the loue of it, wee ſhould forſake heauen, and the pleaſures thereof?</p>
            <p>This world indeed was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the vſe of man, but it is the proper habitation of beaſts. They haue no other home, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they liue or dye, but it. Whereas man is here (with <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi>) but as a <hi>Soiourner.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 47.9.</note> Though hee poſſeſſed here with <hi>Dauid</hi> a whole Kingdome, yet with him ſhould he be termed but a <hi>ſtran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger</hi> here.<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.19.</note> Heauen is his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, that is prepared for him, and the Angels to be their eternall
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:5271:36"/>dwelling place.<note place="margin">Phil. 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>There is his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation</hi> (ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul.</hi>) Is it not then a direct beaſtlineſſe ſo to be enamoured on theſe terreſtriall things, that for the loue of them we would rather remaine in the habitation of bruit beaſts, then remoue vnto the habitations of Angels.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Axiochus</hi> (though he were an Heathen) could before his death be inſtructed by <hi>Platoes</hi> reaſon,<note place="margin">Ar. Plat.</note> 
               <hi>that he did not depart out of this life vnto a death, where he ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of all things, but toward that place where hee ſhould enioy true goods, and where hee ſhould haue pleaſures not mixed with this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall body, but pure, and ſuch as iuſtly deſerue the name of Pleaſures.</hi> And is it not poſſible that this ſhould be perſwaded vnto vs, (who will beare the name of true beleeuers)
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:5271:37"/>to the end that wee might long for it?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</note> But grant this earth to haue as many pleaſures as is poſſible, or as faithfull friends as wee could wiſh. Yet ſhall wee not miſſe, nor deſire theſe things when we are dead. Let vs not thinke that our bodies can dye, and yet then liue. Being dead, we ſhall not haue any members. nor eyes, nor ſmell, nor taſte to vſe theſe things, nor any minde to deſire them. What diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity then will it be, to be without thoſe things which we know not, neede not, nor wiſh not for? Our wife and children will then moue vs no more, then if wee neuer had loued them. <hi>Abraham himſelfe once being dead, remembers vs not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 63.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>and Iſrael knowes vs no more.</hi> Wee likewiſe doe
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:5271:37"/>not know nor remember while we ſleepe, our friends, nor our dayly recreations; yet is there no body therefore that ſhunnes his ſleepe, or flyes from his bed. And wherefore then for that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, ſhould wee feare death, which bereaues vs no more of all theſe things, then our dayly ſleepe is wont to doe?</p>
            <p>One <hi>Demetrius</hi> could boldly ſay, <hi>What deſireſt thou, O Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sen. de pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d.</note> 
               <hi>wilt thou haue my children? beh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld there they bee: wilt thou haue any part of my body, take it freely; yet is it not much which I offer thee, for ere long I ſhall be faine to forſake it all.</hi> This was meruailous well ſaid of a Heathen. But the rich and righteous <hi>Iob,</hi> went farther a great deale: He ſhewed in deed what the other vttered in words. He could ſee his Oxen,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:5271:38"/>his Camels, with all his riches and eſtate, yea his fonnes alſo in diuets manners periſh altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and yet couragiouſly ſay, <hi>The Lord hath giuen, the Lord hath taken,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 1.21.</note> 
               <hi>bleſſed bee the name of the Lord.</hi> If then, theſe men could ſo freely forgoe, and miſſe their neceſſaries in this world, where they yet might haue enioyed them: ſhall we take it grieuouſly to be depriued of our pleaſures, when we ſhall be altogether vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to vſe them?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Praiſe-worthy pleaſure vnne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary.</note> But if any man be loath to dye, in regard of ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable delight, that he taketh in the gouernment of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, or in the orderly education of his children, hee muſt vnderſtand, that if GOD haue called him to the ſame, he alſo beſt knoweth how long hee
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:5271:38"/>hath need of him. And if it pleaſe him ſoone to quit and releaſe him of his good care, and <hi>to giue him a penny,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 20.14.</note> 
               <hi>as well as them that haue borne the burthen of the whole day, and the heat of the Sunne:</hi> what reaſon hath he to complaine? God can finde others more fit, for this his ſeruice, to whom we muſt giue place. <hi>Elyas</hi> ſuppoſed he was left alone,<note place="margin">1 Reg. 19.18.</note> but God had left vnto himſelfe yet ſeauen thouſand in <hi>Iſrael, whoſe knees had not bowed vnto Baal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning our children, we muſt not thinke that their wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare totally depends on the life of their parents. The parents bottle is ſoone empty, and <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mael</hi> might haue dyed euen in his mothers preſence, if GOD had not prouided water for him. <hi>It is hee that openeth his hand,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 145.15.</note> 
               <hi>and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:5271:39"/>ſatisfieth the deſire of euery liuing thing.</hi> Parents are but the ſecond hand, whereby God diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his gifts to his children. They are the lanthorne, through which his diuine care ſhines to the children: take away the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorne, and the light ſhines the clearer. When the Oſtridge forgets her egges,<note place="margin">Iob 39.15.</note> the Lord doth breed them. When the Rauen forſakes her young ones, the Lord feedes them. And when children looſe their terreſtiall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then is it, that he termes himſelfe <hi>a Father of the fatherleſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 68.6.</note> Therefore <hi>Epictetus</hi> was bold to ſay,<note place="margin">An. 3.24.</note> 
               <hi>That among the ſonnes of men there were no Orphanes, but that all haue a father, who ſufficiently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uides for them all continually.</hi> And in another place.<note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.9.</note> 
               <hi>If ſo be, that it be of force enough to make any body
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:5271:39"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iue ſecurely, and without reproach, to be of</hi> Caeſars <hi>kindred. Will it not be ſufficient, to free vs from all ſorrow and feare: to haue God for a Creator, for a Father, for a Prouider?</hi> Let vs put him in truſt with our children; and if after our depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture we will doe them good, let vs liue vprightly our ſelues, and <hi>then none ſhall ſee our children begge their bread,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 37.25.</note> ſaith <hi>Dauid.</hi> Bring them vnto Chriſt,<note place="margin">Math. 19.14.</note> he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them,<note place="margin">Iohn 14.18.</note> and <hi>not leaue them Orphanes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that no delight, nor no good care of this temporall life, ought to make vs vnwilling to dye, for in theſe reſpects no dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing can make vs to inherit ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4. Obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, concerning Iudgement.</note> Laſtly, there is another rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, wherefore the greater, yea the better part of men doe feare
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:5271:40"/>death,<note place="margin">Heb. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.27.</note> they know, <hi>that it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for euery one once to dye, and after this comes Iudgement,</hi> as it is written to the <hi>Hebrewes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this Iudgement is the thing that troubles them, not knowing whether thereby they ſhall aſcend to heauen, or deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend to hell. Alas poore ſoules! When as God by ſome naturall diſeaſe, threatens them with death, then they ſtand quaking: and if a Coronell doth but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe a double pay, or a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines place; how many Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers altogether feareleſſe, are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die (as we may ſee dayly) euen to ruſh on death? Not that this raſhneſſe is wiſedome, for Gods Iudgement deſerues to be feared, yea there is nothing more terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in heauen, nor on earth then it is. For he thereby will <hi>ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:5271:40"/>the ſheepe from the goates;</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing the ſheepe to all eternity, and reiecting the goates for euer.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Death doth not make the Iudgement the heauier.</note> Yet notwithſtanding, we muſt know, that our death neede not to cauſe this feare, for it neither bleſſeth vs, nor condemneth vs, but euer leaues vs as it findes vs.</p>
            <p>The Axe being put to the roote of the tree,<note place="margin">Math. 3.16.</note> doth not by hewing alter any whit, the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the wood.<note place="margin">1 Reg. 5.6.</note> If it light on a thorne-buſh, it hewes downe thornes, fit to make fire withall: If it light on a Cedar tree, it hewes downe Cedar wood, fit for the building of the Temple of the Lord. The Butcher in killing, doth not change goates into ſheepe, nor ſheepe into goates. In like manner, death
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:5271:41"/>neither makes a man worſe nor better, it neither hinders nor far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers him in regard of Gods Iudgement. It is but as a narrow gate (as is fore-told) through the which, both ſheepe and goates muſt paſſe.</p>
            <p>Yet ought euery man chiefly to feare his latter end: <hi>For which way the tree falleth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 11.3.</note> 
               <hi>there ſhall it lye:</hi> But we muſt withall vnderſtand, that it falls commonly that way, that it vſed to leane. We ought then to take heede to this lean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as long as the tree conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth ſtanding, and to bend him that way that we deſire he ſhould fall. For when the fall is approaching, whether it be by axe, ſtorme, or age, it commeth commonly very ſuddainly. Euen ſo it is with man: All the dayes of his life he muſt ſtriue, to leane
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:5271:41"/>that way, that hee lookes or wiſhes to lye. For death (when it comes) ſtrikes the blow in a moment. And man commonly dyes, as hee hath accuſtomed himſelfe to liue. And as hee dyes, ſo ſhal he appeare in Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Death indeede hath a ſting, to wit, ſinne, but it ſtings vs not iuſt at our dying day, but rather through the whole courſe of our life. Therefore be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warneth; Man ſhall reape, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as the ſickle is, which haſtily or ſlowly cuts downe, but as hee hath ſowed, whether it be <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6.7.</note> 
               <hi>or euerlaſting life.</hi> If ſo be then that any one feares that heauenly Iudge, by whom the dead are Iudged according to their workes;<note place="margin">Apoc. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> what is this to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:5271:42"/>death? To ſowe and to worke, are properties of life, not of death; and therefore ought eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one to tremble at his life, not at his death.</p>
            <p>Yet may ſome ſay it is natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall (with <hi>Adam</hi> in Paradiſe) for a man to hide himſelfe ſo long as he can from Gods voyce. It may be naturall, but it is not auaileable. For firſt, we cannot by running ſo out-runne death, but that it will ouer-take vs. Secondly, though wee could here on earth prolong our life ſome fourty or fifty yeares, yet it were but to ſmall purpoſe. <hi>Though a man liue</hi> (ſayes <hi>Syrachs</hi> ſonne) <hi>a hundred yeares,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ecclus. 18.6.</note> 
               <hi>it is but as a drop of water vnto the ſea, and a grauell ſtone in compariſon of the ſand; ſo are a thouſand yeares, to the day of eternity.</hi> Therefore <hi>Iacob</hi>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:5271:42"/>called his dayes of a hundred and thirty yeares,<note place="margin">Gen. 47.</note> 
               <hi>fewe and euill.</hi> Thirdly, the longer a worldling (who chiefly dreads death) with vexation ſhunnes it, he doth not onely the longer liue here in paine, but the more alſo he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth the number of his ſins, and conſequently drawes on him the fearefuller Iudgement. Yea, the burthen of dayly ſinnes, doth ſo graciouſly ouer-load the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of godly men, that it euen makes them weary of this life, and cauſeth them with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul,</hi> to cry out, <hi>Miſerable man that I am,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7.14.</note> 
               <hi>who ſhall releaſe me of this body of death?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if any man ſhunne death, and feareth the Iudgement, as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous of further time to amend his life hereafter, let ſuch an one know, that he that deferres his
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:5271:43"/>amendment, may as well growe worſe, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> better. The firſt world obtain'd of God a hundred and twenty yeares toward their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion, yet it nothing auayled them, they were almoſt all drowned in the floud.<note place="margin">Gen. 6.3.</note> 
               <hi>Yea E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch, in the meane while he walked before God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 5.24.</note> 
               <hi>God tooke him, and hee was ſeene no more</hi> (ſaith Moſes) <hi>leſt that wickedneſſe ſhould alter his vnderſtanding, or deceit beguile his ſoule,</hi> ſayes the booke of <hi>Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that the taking away of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch</hi> out of this world, was a more certaine way for him to auoyde the fierceneſſe of Gods Iudgement, then if he had liued longer in danger of being miſled. Thus wee ſee then that death cannot be any hinderance vnto vs, at the day of Iudgement, and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:5271:43"/>that in that reſpect wee haue no reaſon to feare it.</p>
            <p>Seeing then that death is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and generall,<note place="margin">Concluſion.</note> and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the will of God, ſeeing that of its owne nature, it can hurt vs neither in ſoule nor in body, nor will ſuffer vs to long after terreſtriall things, nor ſhall be any hinderance vnto vs at the day of Iudgement. We ſuppoſe that it is hereby ſufficiently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated, that by nature it is not euill, nor can any way pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice vs. Therefore ought wee more to ſhunne the feare of death, then death it ſelfe. For (once more, and for the laſt, to vſe the words of a Philoſopher) commonly <hi>when we feare the death of the body, and by all meanes ſhunne the ſame, wee neglect altogether the death of the ſoule.</hi> I conclude
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:5271:44"/>therefore with the fore-named words of Chriſt our Sauiour, <hi>Feare not thoſe that kill the body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">How our time is ordained by God, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed by man.</note> With which couragious ſpeech, we would faine here con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, but being that death doth aſſaile vs diuers manner of wayes, and that it is a queſtion ready almoſt in euery mans mouth, whether a man can ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten his life, or dye before his time, wee will touch this in a word or two, as an addition vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our former diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>We ſay then with <hi>Iob, Man hath his appointed time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 14.5.</note> 
               <hi>the number of his moneths is with God; He hath ſet a limit,</hi> (that he muſt attaine) <hi>and that he muſt not paſſe.</hi> This diuine decree, and immutable will, is hid from mens eyes, yet remaines conſtant, and comes to paſſe at his due time. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:5271:44"/>publiquely by the reuealed hand of GOD. Whereby he prolonged <hi>Lots,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 16.19.</note> 
               <hi>and his daughters liues, by withdrawing them out of the Citie,</hi> which he meant to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume with fire. Sometimes by that which wee call chance, though the hand of God be in it too; <hi>For thus an arrowe ſhot at a uenture by a Syrian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Reg. 22.34.</note> 
               <hi>lighted betweene the ioynts of his harneſſe, and ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the life of that King:</hi> Of whom GOD had fore-told, that hee ſhould not returne home aliue. Commonly through mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>that cauſeth the weake in their youth to dye by ſickneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 22.15.</note> 
               <hi>and ſuſtaines the life of the ſtrong, till like a ſheafe of corne they come into the barne in their ſeaſon.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 5.26.</note> And likewiſe by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other meanes.</p>
            <p>Sometimes God doth effect his ſecret decree by a publique
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:5271:45"/>prolonging, or elſe a contracting of time. When he granted time to the corrupt men of the firſt world (which he would bring to naught) of an hundred and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty yeares:<note place="margin">Gen. 6.3.</note> then this prolonging of time, brought them to the vniuerſall flood, as it was before appointed by God. Againe, <hi>if for the Elects ſake the dayes ſhall be ſhortned</hi> (as many doe conceiue) then ſhall this ſhortning bring the world to the vniuerſall fire appointed by God.<note place="margin">Math. 24.22.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And according to this recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of time, man himſelfe may ſometimes be the meanes of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing his life. Doth not God ſpeake by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and to <hi>Salomon</hi> alſo:<note place="margin">Deut. 5.23.</note> 
               <hi>If you walke in my wayes, ſo that you keepe my commandement,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Reg 3.14.</note> 
               <hi>I will giue you long life.</hi> Yea, God puts the meanes of prolonging
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:5271:45"/>our life in our owne hands. This was apparent in the wilderneſſe by the fierie Serpents, whereas they were only ſaued and healed of their venomous bites, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held the brazen Serpent. The King <hi>Ezekias</hi> likewiſe obtained by his prayers and teares,<note place="margin">Numb. 21.8.</note> that God <hi>added vnto his dayes fifteene yeares.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Reg. 20.6.</note> Was not then his laſt day certainly preordained of God? Yea, but it was alſo his immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table good pleaſure, that the King ſhould euen thus entreat, and begge of him theſe laſt fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene yeares.</p>
            <p>And now alſo whoſoeuer he be, that through prayers &amp; Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, is releas'd of any ſore diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, hee ought not fooliſhly to boaſt, that he ſhould haue liued out his time, that was appointed for him, though he had not vſed
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:5271:46"/>the meanes: but he ought rather freely to acknowledge, that by theſe meanes his life hath beene pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſerued.</p>
            <p>Secondly, man is ſometimes alſo occaſion of the ſhortning his dayes. Hence it is that the Kingly Prophet ſaid, <hi>Bloudie and deceitfull men ſhall not liue out halfe their dayes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 55.23.</note> And who will not ſay,<note place="margin">Sam. 31.4.</note> that <hi>Saul</hi> and his Armour-bearer (who ſtabbed themſelues) were an occaſion of ſhortning their owne liues. As alſo that whoſoeuer (after <hi>Moſes</hi> had giuen warning of it) <hi>ſhould touch Mount Sinai,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 19.4.</note> 
               <hi>while the Lord was on it,</hi> ſhould caſt himſelfe into the mouth of death? Euen as now, if any man of ſet purpoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits ſome haynous offence, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to puniſhment of death by the lawes of the land, is it not
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:5271:46"/>his owne fault that hee is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaued of life? Hee can accuſe no body for it, but himſelfe. And therefore the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſo oft repeates it, <hi>His blood be vpon his owne head:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 1.16.</note> that is to ſay, the fault is his owne, and it is good reaſon, hee ſhould ſuffer for it.</p>
            <p>Wherefore alſo God doth not iudge, or examine our workes, whether they be good or bad, by that his ſecret counſell which hee hath not reuealed vnto vs. But his Iuſtice requires, that hee ſhould reward the well-doers, and puniſh the offenders, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that law, and that his good pleaſure, which hee hath reuealed vnto vs all. Hee hath manifeſtly commanded,<note place="margin">Exod. 20.15.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill.</hi> According to which law, he wills alſo, that who ſo
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:5271:47"/>ſlayes a man,<note place="margin">Deut. 27.24.25.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall be put to death.</hi> And withall, he cauſeth him to be accurſed, that <hi>takes reward to ſlay an innocent perſon.</hi> If God then cauſe the murtherer to be executed, as guilty of another mans death; who dares op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and ſay, that Gods decree of the dead mans time could ſuffer him to liue no longer? Should wee not rather ſay, that he is pittifully deceaſed before his time? Not before that time, which the omniſcient GOD in his ſecret counſell, hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for euery one in particular, but before that time which hee hath ordained for humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in generall. Which time was before intimated vnto vs out of the ninetieth Pſalme. Hence that Ieſus <hi>Syrachs</hi> ſonne dares ſay,<note place="margin">Ecclus. 50.24.</note> 
               <hi>That enuie and wrath
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:5271:47"/>ſhorten the life, and carefulneſſe bringeth old age before the time.</hi> Thus alſo was it told <hi>Iob,</hi> that <hi>wicked men are cut downe out of time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 14.5.</note> though hee himſelfe was certaine, that God had <hi>appointed man his bounds. But it is not for vs</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>to know the times and ſeaſons,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 1.7.</note> 
               <hi>which the Father hath put in his owne power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For indeed (to ſpeake pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly according to the nature of God) his de-vnitie hath no par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of times. Wee muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold one yeare after another, and when wee haue attained to the ſecond, the firſt is fled away from vs. But all our times, and all things that are done in euery one of them, ſtand and abide perpetually together in Gods ſight. So that betweene his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering, and our accompliſhing,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:5271:48"/>there is (before him) no ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion nor ſtarting away of any time. With him there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yeſterday nor to morrow, but eternally, to day. Yet will we not here deale further, with theſe myſteries, but learne of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 27.29.</note> 
               <hi>That the things that are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed, belong vnto vs and our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</hi> And it is fitting, that wee ſubmiſly containe our time-ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, within the limits of our owne apprehenſion.</p>
            <p>Our Lord Ieſus, when the Romane Gouernour told him, that he <hi>had power to crucifie him, and power to releaſe him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 19.11.</note> 
               <hi>did not oppoſe him,</hi> but in his anſwer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, <hi>that this power was giuen him from aboue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this then being pondered, wee muſt iudge according to Gods law, and freely conclude,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:5271:48"/>that a man may ſometimes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long or ſhorten his owne, or another mans life. And in that reſpect (following the phraſe of <hi>Iob, Dauid,</hi> and the ſonne of <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rach</hi>) we may well ſay, that ſuch a man is departed before his time.</p>
            <p>If the our life and death be in our power, and if affections haue thus their free courſe: how is Gods decree then fulfilled at his appointed time? Surely moſt preciſely, and euen by our owne deedes, though oftentimes without our knowledge, yea ſometimes againſt our will. Whereupon the Euangeliſt ſayes, (after the rehearſall of the ſlaughter of the Infants at <hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leem) that then was fulfilled that which was ſpoken by the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 2.17.</note> And as touching this matter, it is with
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:5271:49"/>vs, euen as with a ſtreame that retaines his naturall and free courſe, though by the Miller it be vſed to driue his Mill, which hee conueniently grindes his wheat by, which within dores he hath thereunto ordered. Yea, if any body ſhould wickedly p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wre out a deale of ſtinking wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into this ſtreame, or ſhould altogether poyſon the ſame, this offence deſerues puniſhment, yet the naturall deſcent of this dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and poyſoned water, will grinde the Millers corne, and not infect his meale with any kinde of pollution. Euen ſo doth God vſe and ſteere all our, both good and bad actions to his preor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained (though in reſpect of vs concealed from vs) intents.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Gods proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence doth not excuſe mans wickedneſſe.</note> But doth not this preordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God then, patronize all
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:5271:49"/>mans miſdeedes? God forbid, Gods prouidence is no cloake for mans iniquity. If a Fencer ſhould finde his skilfull Scholler at his weapon, with ſome vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfull Clowne, he ſoone could perceiue, that hee would be the death of him. Yea, he ſees the ſtroke falling, as wee may ſay, and therefore he ſharply prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits and threatens his Scholler. Howbeit, the Scholler notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ching for his beſt opportunity, findes it, and giues the other his mortall wound. Shall this make him guiltleſſe to his Maſter, if hee tell him, that this of neceſſity muſt ſo chance, becauſe hee vndoubtedly fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſawe it? Yea moreouer, if hee vpbraide his Maſter, that it was in his power to haue laide him faſt in fetters, and ſo (if it had
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:5271:50"/>pleaſed him) to haue hindred that murther, might not his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter deſeruedly anſwer him thus? If thou hadſt beene a beaſt, I would haue curbed thy body with chaines, but I would vſe thee like a man that ought to keepe his Spiri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in orderly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection, and to this intent haue I vſed all manner of conuenient meanes with thee, as by entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, by lawes, by threatnings. Haſt thou neglected all thoſe, and wilt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hou not be ruled, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe thou be curbed as a wilde Beare? I will lay hands then on thee, and puniſh thee as a beaſt. Should not this young Fencer be faine to confeſſe, that he had deſerued this fierce vſage? Indeede, much leſſe can any man excuſe his miſdeeds, by laying the fault on GODS
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:5271:50"/>prouidence or conuinencie.</p>
            <p>Or ſay, that God out of our euill, can extract good, yet is man forbidden,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.2.</note> 
               <hi>to doe euill that good may come thereof.</hi> For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, though the enuie of the Phariſes, the betraying of <hi>Iudas,</hi> and the iniuſtice of <hi>Pilate</hi> were meanes of bringing to paſſe (by the cruell death that they put Chriſt vnto) mans reconciliation in ſuch a manner, and at ſuch a time,<note place="margin">Act. 4.28.</note> 
               <hi>as Gods counſell had before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined it ſhould bee done.</hi> Yet doth our Sauiour neuertheleſſe cry,<note place="margin">Mar. 14.21.</note> 
               <hi>Woe vnto that man, by whom the Son of man is betrayed.</hi> He was not onely puniſhed according to his deſerts, but was alſo moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably his owne executioner.</p>
            <p>But was not this alſo Gods worke? It was, and <hi>Amos</hi> ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the queſtion, <hi>If there ſhall be
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:5271:51"/>any euill in a Citie, and the Lord hath not done it?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos 3.6.</note> Yet this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall working of God, neither ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth God guilty, nor excuſeth man of any euill. It is with God in ſome ſort, as it is with a man, that thro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gh the bellowes blowes the winde in the Organ pipes. Hee cauſes falſe ſtrokes (when a bungler is at the keyes) as well to ſound, as the muſicall, notes when the skilfull Organiſt playes. For without this winde can no bungler either heare his owne vnskilfulneſſe, or manifeſt it to others. Yet is not he that blowes in fault, the bungler vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfully abuſeth the ſound of a good Organ. In like manner all the force, that our ſoule hath to moue it ſelfe or our members to ſtirre themſelues, comes onely from God. But the peruerting
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:5271:51"/>of theſe, to the plotting or act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of euill proceedes from our ſelues.</p>
            <p>Againe,<note place="margin">Comfort out of Gods Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence.</note> is the knowledge then of Gods prouidence and predeſtination vnprofitable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs? This is the onely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of wiſe and godly men. For theſe doe endeauour to obey the reuealed will of God, and with great content of minde commit the euent vnto him, both of this life, and of all their actions in the ſame. Yea, they proceede farther. If here they enioy a happy life, or if they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue any kinde of benefit, or delight here on earth, they are the more thankfull, becauſe they know it befalls them through the prouidence of the Almighty and reioyce in his fauour. If their life chance to be croſſed
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:5271:52"/>or ſhortned any kinde of way, though they ſee it lights on them by the hatred of men. Yet the more willingly they endure it, becauſe they know it is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret will of their God, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Father, who is onely good and perfectly wiſe. And it ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficeth them, <hi>that the Lord harke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>and heareth them.</hi> Hence al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo it commeth to paſſe, that in all troubles of life and death, in all blindneſſe of minde, in all weakeneſſe of faith, in all angui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes of ſpirit, they are wont to caſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues ſubmiſly into the ſweet and fatherly armes of this diuine prouidence, <hi>and ſo commit their wayes vnto the Lord their God with a ſtedfaſt confidenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 37.5.</note> that hee will effect all things for their good.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:5271:52"/>
               <head>THE SECOND PART <hi>CONCERNING DEATH.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hich we intend now to produce, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoureth to ſhew that Death is not only not preiudiciall, but euen profitable vnto Gods Elect; and that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it ought to be welcome vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. For vnto them it is a paſſage to eternall bliſſe. The which can onely be taught and declared vnto vs, by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:5271:53"/>of Gods word, which now muſt be our onely guide.</p>
               <p>But ſeeing that ſickneſſe is commonly a fore-runner of death, we will firſt endeauour to ſhew, how both before, and at the time of the approach there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, wee ought to prepare our houſe, our body, and our ſoule. Secondly, we will enquire how wee may diſarme Death of its ſting, and ſo arme our ſelues, that it ſhall not be able to hurt our ſoules. Thirdly, wee ſhall ſeeke to ſtrengthen the feeble in faith, and to comfort the troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led conſciences in their aſſaults. And laſtly, we hope to make it manifeſt, that we ought to long for the end of this life, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſundry honours, and ioyes, that expect vs after it. Which foure points, wee pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:5271:53"/>in order as they follow to diſcuſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Sickneſſe from God.</note> Whether then ſickneſſe doe faſten on vs, through an exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall bad ayre, or ſome intern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all diſtemper of blood by the ſword, or by the infection of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men, or the ſting or furie of wilde beaſts, by dead palſies, by miſcarryings, or vnfortunate childe-birthes, or by any other meanes or miſchance whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, wee muſt vnderſtand that God maketh theſe and all other, manifeſted meanes his ſeruants, to execute on vs his ſecret will.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Sickneſſe through ſin.</note> The cauſe for which diſeaſes are ſent, is our ſinne, as it is ſet downe at large in the fif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> booke of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 28.</note> and is confirmed by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul,</hi> where he ſaith to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians, <hi>For this cauſe, many are weake and ſickly among you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.29.</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:5271:54"/>they take the Lords ſupper vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily.</hi> Yet is it not thus alwayes. For the blindneſſe of that man that Chriſt gaue ſight vnto, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell him not either for his owne, <hi>or his Parents ſinne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 9.3.</note> 
                  <hi>but that the workes of God ſhould be made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in him:</hi> But generally, <hi>he that ſinneth before his Maker, muſt fall into the hands of the Phiſitian</hi> (ſaith <hi>Eccleſiaſticus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ecclus. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>15.</note>)</p>
               <p>But what ought wee to doe when ſickneſſe aſſaileth vs?<note place="margin">1 <hi>Point.</hi> Preparation of our houſe.</note> Yea, what ought wee at all times to doe, that Death may not be hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto vs? We muſt prepare our ſelues well againſt the ſame. This did <hi>Ezechias</hi> the King learne of that Prophet that ſaid vnto him,<note place="margin">Eſ. 38.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Set thy houſe in order, for thou ſhalt die, and not liue.</hi> If ſo be that God commanded him for to ſet his houſe in order, who
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:5271:54"/>had yet fifteene yeares to liue we can by no meanes procraſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate it without great danger, who each houre may expect to heare with the rich man in the Goſpell,<note place="margin">Luk. 12.20.</note> 
                  <hi>This night ſhall thy ſoule be required of thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore to conceiue this aright, we muſt vnderſtand that this preparation is three-fold, to wit, of our houſhold and earthly poſſeſſions, of our body, &amp; prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally of our ſoule.</p>
               <p>Touching our houſhold or heires, wee are not onely bound in duty to keepe them in good order, and peace while we liue, but likewiſe ſo to fore-caſt all things, that we may leaue peace with them after our departure. <hi>If any prouide not for thoſe of his owne houſe</hi> (ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>he is worſe then an Infidell.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 5.8.</note>
               </p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:5271:55"/>
               <p>Therefore is euery one of vs bound at all times, but eſpecially in the time of ſickneſſe, to ſtriue to end all quarrells, and ſuites with his aduerſaries, to reueale all doubtfull things, to his friends, and beſides to make a plaine and lawfull partition, of his goods by his laſt will. And he muſt not deferre this, till hee waxe olde,<note place="margin">Gen. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.1.</note> as <hi>Iſaac</hi> did, who ſtayed till he was blinde, and ſo, at the inſtant, could not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the deceit of his wife. And much leſſe till he be ſicke, or at deaths dore. For this laſt time will buſie a ſicke man enough, in reconciling his ſoule to God. Hee that firſt goes about to take leaue of his friends, when the ſhip is putting off, doth often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times looſe his vovage by it. And hee that at the laſt paſpe is
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:5271:55"/>encombred with the world, ſtands in danger of forgetting heauen. The woman that was carefull for <hi>Sodome,</hi> when ſhee could walke to the place of her ſafety,<note place="margin">Gen. 29.26.</note> remained ſtanding by the way. And that <hi>Achitophel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 17.23.</note> 
                  <hi>who ſet his houſe in order but iuſt before the houre of his death,</hi> (as the Scripture telleth vs) had no great leaſure to thinke on God, appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by his wicked end, which is ſet downe for our inſtruction and admonition.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Preparation of the body.</note> Touching our body, the care of the ſame is alſo committed vnto vs, yea enioyned vs. And leaprous <hi>Naaman</hi> teacheth vs, that he that is diligent in enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,<note place="margin">1 Reg. 2.1.</note> may oft finde remedy for his diſeaſe. And in this reſpect <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi> his ſiſters are much to bee commended, who preſently
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:5271:56"/>ſent to Chriſt to come and heale their brothers corporall diſeaſe.<note place="margin">Ioh. 11.3.</note> Wee alſo in our weake and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing eſtate, ought to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for our body needfull meanes, according as our weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhall require, and our abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity may afford: For God hath created many things to releeue our infirmity withall. This S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> manifeſts vnto vs,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.23.</note> where he charges <hi>Timothy</hi> to vſe a little wine, for his ſtomacks ſake. We muſt alſo ſend for the Phyſitian,<note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 2.17.</note> for the ſicke haue neede of him, as Chriſt witneſſeth. For God that inflicts ſickneſſe oft by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall meanes, vſeth alſo to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe vs thereof by externall remedies. So <hi>Eſay</hi> commanded <hi>Plaiſters of figges</hi> to be made for King <hi>Ezechias,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſ. 38.21.</note> and layde vpon the boyle, <hi>that he might recouer.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:5271:56"/>
               <p>We ought then to take care of our ſicke members, and not to trouble or ouer-loade our weake head too much with the moleſtations of trade, or world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affaires:<note place="margin">Ecclus. 30.16.</note> 
                  <hi>For a ſound body is better then much riches.</hi> Nor yet too too much to grieue our lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing heart with diſcomfort, in regard of that our preſent af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, but we muſt doe good to our ſelues, comfort our heart, <hi>and remooue ſorrow farre from vs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ecclus. 30.23.</note> and commend the euent vnto our heauenly Father.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The enduring of anguiſhes.</note> And although in the meane while our paines almoſt intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably doe grieue vs, yet we muſt know certainly that wee receiue them all from the hands of that good God, who heretofore hath afforded vs many more ioyfull dayes of health, &amp; conſequently
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:5271:57"/>we may therefore ſay with <hi>Iob; Haue we receiued good at the hands of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob 2.10.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſhall we not receiue euill.</hi> And yet this chaſtiſement is not euill. <hi>No chaſtening for the preſent ſeemeth to be ioyous,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 12.10.</note> 
                  <hi>but grieuous.</hi> (We read to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi>) <hi>How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit afterwards, it yeeldeth the peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able fruit of righteouſneſſe vnto them which are exerciſed thereby. For whom the Lord loueth he chaſteneth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 12.6.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſcourgeth euery ſonne whom hee receiueth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If then wee will aſſure our ſelues that wee are Gods deare children, and ſpirituall members of one head, that in this world with much anguiſh was cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; wee muſt following the command &amp; example of Chriſt, <hi>take vp our croſſe and follow him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mar. 10.21.</note> He doth not command vs to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume that Croſſe which euery
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:5271:57"/>one would chuſe himſelfe, but that which the diuine Proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence doth make ours. And vnder the ſame wee muſt not heartleſly lye downe, but cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiouſly beare it, and not beare it onely, for this euen the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates doe againſt their wills, but take it vp as from Gods hand, and for his ſake patiently endure it: But how farre, and how long muſt we doe this? Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands vs to follow him. Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did he beare his? vnto his death. Euen ſo farre alſo muſt we beare ours, if it pleaſe him ſo long to loade vs therewith. Yet by the way, let our ſoule caſt her eye on the Croſſe of Chriſt, and we ſhall behold one <hi>Simon</hi> a <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renean,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 23.26.</note> who carrying it a while, followes him. If ſo be then that our Sauiour (who was God) was
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:5271:58"/>by a man refreſhed in bearing his Croſſe, farre more hope may we (that are ſilly mortalls) haue, that we ſhall be eaſed in bearing our Croſſe. But what was the vſe of this his Croſſe? On the ſame he gaue vp his ſoule into the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ands of his heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and finiſhed the worke of our reconciliation. And S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> as a ſpirituall member of Chriſt his body, <hi>filled vp in his ſufferings that which was behinde of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions of Chriſt:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Col. 1.24.</note> So alſo muſt we hope and wiſh that our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction may be vnto vs, as a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient meanes <hi>of preſenting our bodies a liuing,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 12.1.</note> 
                  <hi>holy, and</hi> (through Chriſt) <hi>an acceptable ſacrifice vnto God:</hi> which we commonly bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter performe in miſery then in a pleaſure. <hi>For in trouble doe wee ſeeke God</hi> (ſaith <hi>Eſay.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay 26.16.</note>)</p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:5271:58"/>
               <p>If therefore it pleaſe God for a long time to viſite vs with his common rods of agues, lame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the gowt, the ſtone, or other ſore grieuances, let vs not be diſcomforted, much leſſe be rebellious.<note place="margin">Iob 1.21.</note> Let vs alſo with <hi>Iob</hi> take heede wee doe not ſinne through impatience. Let vs be eſpecially inſtructed by the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Thiefe, that could ſay in the midſt of his paine.<note place="margin">Luk. 23.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Wee receiue the due reward of our deedes:</hi> and conſider that our Sauiour hath ſuffered farre greater torments in ſoule and body, though (as the ſame party ſayes) <hi>hee himſelfe had done nothing amiſſe.</hi> Hence we alſo in our anguiſh haue great reaſon to thanke God, that it hath pleaſed him to lay the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie puniſhments which wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued on his Sonne, and by this
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:5271:59"/>his fatherly chaſtiſement to withdraw vs from the world, and to call vs home vnto him.</p>
               <p>Let vs alſo freely hope, that he that hath ſmitten vs, <hi>will binde our ſores vp againe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſ. 6.1.</note> Yea it may bee that hee comes now with ſtripes to heale vs, if not the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, yet the ſoule, which is more infected then the body, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires more curing, then our ſelues can conceiue. Let <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> teach vs, <hi>that faithfull are the wounds of friends,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 27.6.</note> 
                  <hi>but the kiſſes of an enemie are deceitfull.</hi> Hence ought we more to reioyce in this viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of God, then if the deuill came and fla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tered vs with the whole worlds proſperity. The apoſtle alſo termeth <hi>that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 1.12.</note> 
                  <hi>that endureth temptation: For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>when he is tried, he ſhal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the crown of life.</hi> Let this then
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:5271:59"/>moue vs to patience, and let it be our greateſt comfort in our ſoreſt griefe.</p>
               <p>But (may ſome heere ſay) though it be true indeede,<note place="margin">The difference of the wicked and the good in corrections.</note> that God chaſtens thoſe children, whom he makes his owne, yet it followeth not that therefore he makes all thoſe his, whom he chaſteneth, For wee reade, that <hi>God doth rebuke and deſtroy the heathens through many plagues.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 9.6.</note> How then ſhall I know whether this heauenly Sheepheard ſtrike at me with his Crooke, as at a ſtraying Sheepe, which he dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth home to the Sheepe-fold, or as at a Woolfe which hee frights away.</p>
               <p>This a man may perceiue by himſelfe, according as hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiues and makes vſe of the blowe. Gods ſtroke is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:5271:60"/>what like the Pills, which Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians vſe to preſcribe. Vnruly men turne and chewe them in their mouth, till the bitterneſſe of them doth make them euen to loath them, and at the laſt, with great anguiſh (though no benefit) ſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them out againe. But the wiſer ſort knowing that the Phyſitian thereby doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour to recouer their health, ſwallowe them without taſting them, and let them worke in their body.</p>
               <p>Euen ſo the Reprobates, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider in their diſeaſes nothing, but the externall troubles, and onely take care how they may be deliuered from them. They are alwayes impatient, murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring againſt God (if they looke ſo high at leaſt) or againſt them onely which God doth vſe as
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:5271:60"/>inſtruments of their puniſhment. Neither are they mollified here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, that they may returne vnto their God. <hi>Though you ſhould bray a foole in a Morter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 27.22.</note> 
                  <hi>yet will not his fooliſhneſſe depart from him,</hi> ſayes the wiſe King. And this was apparen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the hard puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yet ſtil hard hearted <hi>Pharaoh.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.32.</note> And <hi>Ahaz</hi> (ſayes the Scripture) in his troubles <hi>treſpaſſed yet more againſt the Lord.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Chro. 28, 23.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But the children of God (on the contrary) receiue th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> blowe as from the hand of their Father, and blame nothing more then their ſinnes that deſerue puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as the cauſe thereof. They know that God doth all things for their beſt, and ſo haue their eyes fixed on the heavenly bliſſe promiſed to the patient, that they thereby endure or ſwallow
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:5271:61"/>downe their paines much the eaſier. And therefore they ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther turne themſelues to their God; for the ſame King ſaith, <hi>When the wiſe is rebuked, he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth knowledge.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 21.11.</note> Hee perceiueth that hee muſt part from his miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deedes.<note place="margin">Ion 2.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Hee cryes vnto the Lord with Ionah in his affliction.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Chro. 35.12.</note> 
                  <hi>He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeecheth the Lord his God</hi> (<hi>with</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes) <hi>in his diſtreſſe, and humbleth himſelfe greatly, and his ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is heard. I haue ſinned</hi> (ſaith he) with <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 24.17.</note> in his peſtilence, or in any other ſickneſſe. And with the ſame <hi>Dauid</hi> hee is not aſhamed afterwards to confeſſe, <hi>that before hee was afflicted he went aſtray,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 119 64.</note> 
                  <hi>but now hee keepes GODS word.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To be ſhort, the viſitations of the Lord, be oft one and the ſame, both to the good and to
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:5271:61"/>the bad: but the euent is cleane contrary, and may well be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled vnto the accurſed wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which the Prieſt vpon occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the husbands iealouſie, gaue the women ſometime to drinke. This water was bitter in the mouth vnto all, but being taken (ſayes the Scripture) <hi>the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed did ſwell of it,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Num. 5.27.28.</note> 
                  <hi>but it could not hurt thoſe that were cleane.</hi> Yea, the chaſte ones gaue their huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands occaſion by this triall, to loue them better then before. Wee reade in one ſelfe-ſame Chapter,<note place="margin">Act. 12.7. &amp; 23</note> 
                  <hi>that the Angell of the Lord ſmote Peter, and the Angell of the Lord ſmote Herode.</hi> But the one was thereby raiſed vp, and deliuered from death, and the other gaue vp the ghoſt. Euen ſo are the better ſort by the hand of God raiſed vp out of the ſleepe
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:5271:62"/>of ſinne to be deliuered from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall death, and the wicked are conſumed by their endleſſe grudgings, euen till their dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing day.</p>
               <p>This is then the difference, Gods enemies endure the croſſe indeede, but reape no benefit thereby, but paine and domage, whereas Gods friends take their croſſe from him, and ſo beare it, that theſe bodily paines <hi>turne to their good.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom 8.28.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Now concerning the ſoule, though we ſpeake of it laſt,<note place="margin">Preparation of the ſoule.</note> yet ought we in our ſickneſſe firſt to begin with it, following the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the afore-named King. Hee in his weakeneſſe did not firſt conſult with the Phyſitians, <hi>but turned his face from the people to the wall,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 38.2.</note> and there betweene God &amp; himſelfe began to pray,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:5271:62"/>and ro rip vp his offences, and to bewayle them. And after that hee committed him to bee cured. <hi>Dauid</hi> alſo firſt prayeth, <hi>Deliuer me from my tranſgreſsions,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 39 8.11.</note> 
                  <hi>and afterwards remooue thy ſtroke away from me.</hi> This order doth the ſonne of <hi>Syrach</hi> fitly ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs, in foure parts. <hi>Pray vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord. Ceaſe to ſinne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ecclus. 38.9 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Make a fat offering, and then giue place to the Phyſitian.</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iames</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith alſo,<note place="margin">Iam. 5.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Confeſſe your faults one to another, and pray one for another that you may be healed.</hi> Wee ought therefore in the firſt place, (yea before we can offer vnto God with a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, the calues of our lips, (as Chriſt by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Mathew</hi> teacheth vs) <hi>to endeauour to be reconciled to our brother who hath ought againſt vs.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 5.24.</note> And to be ready to forgiue
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:5271:63"/>our neighbours all offences com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt vs. Secondly, wee muſt alſo openly confeſſe our manifold tranſgreſſions, as occaſions of all ſickneſſes, and ſay with <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 7.15.</note> 
                  <hi>What I would, that doe I not; but what I hate, that doe I.</hi> And with <hi>Dauid,</hi> wee muſt pray vnto God continually,<note place="margin">Pſal. 38.</note> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe with <hi>Ezechias</hi> vprightneſſe of life.<note place="margin">Eſay 38.10.</note> Concerning the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fice, <hi>Dauid</hi> confirmes it, ſaying, <hi>Bleſſed is hee that conſidereth the poore,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 41.1.</note> 
                  <hi>the Lord will deliuer him in the day of trouble.</hi> This muſt the ſoule ruminate, when man is ſurprized with ſickneſſe. <hi>Moſes</hi> knew well enough how much it behooued well to prepare the ſoule againſt death, when hee ſaid, <hi>So teach vs to number our dayes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 90.12.</note> 
                  <hi>that we may apply our hearts vnto wiſedome:</hi> That hee muſt
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:5271:63"/>dye, and that his dayes were nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable, nature taught him, but conſiderately to meditate on death, or day by day euen num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring them; to prepare himſelfe againſt the ſame, that God muſt teach him, of whom he requeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it by prayer.</p>
               <p>Our Lord Ieſus Chriſt know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how needfull this meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on would be vnto vs,<note place="margin">Neceſſity of ſpeedy repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</note> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that many times we are ſo ſuddainly ſnatcht out of this world, that wee haue no time once to thinke on ought, ceaſeth not to admoniſh vs, that wee ſhould be continually buſied hereabout. Teaching vs ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time by fore-warning vs, as where he ſayes, <hi>Be yee ready,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 24.44.</note> 
                  <hi>for in ſuch an houre as you thinke not, the ſonne of man commeth.</hi> Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by way of inſtruction,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:5271:64"/>
                  <hi>Be yee your ſelues</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>like vnto them that waite for their Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 12.36.</note> 
                  <hi>that when he commeth and knocketh, yee may open vnto him immediatly.</hi> And ſometimes by ſimilitudes, as that of the fiue fooliſh Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins,<note place="margin">Math. 25.10.</note> that neuer went about to fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>niſh their Lampes with oyle, before they heard that the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome was comming. And fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, by fearefull examples of the dayes of <hi>Noah</hi> and <hi>Lot;</hi> In which (ſayes the Scripture) men were ſo buſied <hi>with eating and drinking,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 17.26.28.</note> 
                  <hi>marrying of wiues, buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſelling, planting and build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> that they did not thinke on their end, vntill that firſt <hi>the flood of water;</hi> and after that, <hi>the fire rained downe from heauen, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed them all.</hi> Which admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions, though they haue an eye to the ſuddaine comming of the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:5271:64"/>day of Iudgement, yet ſeeing that the temporall dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs to that eſtate, wherein the Iudge at the laſt day ſhall finde and confirme vs; we are warned by Chriſt, to be ſo well prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againſt the aſſault of this death, that we through the ſame may not paſſe into the ſecond, and euerlaſting death.</p>
               <p>But if ſo be that thoſe which ſpent their time in buying and ſelling, and other lawfull affaires, were ſo conſumed in GODS wrath: what may others expect, that ſpend euen their whole time in things vtterly vnlawfull? If thoſe miſſed the right way, how ſhall theſe enter into that gate which leades vnto eternall life; which is ſo ſtraight,<note place="margin">Math. 7.13.</note> 
                  <hi>that fewe there be that finde it.</hi> Or doth a man in his extreamity, thinke to
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:5271:65"/>find ſome precious thing, which in his ſtrong health hee neuer looked after? Doth hee thinke after his departure, Royally to be entertained by that King, with whom in his life time hee neuer ſought to be acquainted? This is ſomewhat too late, and chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth very ſeldome. Let no man therefore continue in his impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, in hope to conuert himſelfe to God on his death-bed. This preſumption is the moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous poyſon that the deuill can miniſter to any man. We muſt learne out of the holy Scripture, that he that all his life-time hath beene <hi>a thorne-Buſh or a Thiſtle,</hi> doth not vſually afterwards bring foorth Figges or Grapes. And <hi>that the tree that bringeth not forth good fruits,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 7.16.19.</note> 
                  <hi>is hewen downe, and caſt into the fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:5271:65"/>
               <p>Therefore let vs with Ieſus, <hi>Syrachs</hi> ſonne, <hi>while wee are yet young, ere euer we goe aſtray,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ecclus. 51.13.</note> 
                  <hi>deſire wiſedom openly in our prayers. Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thy ſelfe</hi> (ſaith hee alſo) <hi>before thou be ſicke, and in the time of ſinnes ſhew repentance. Let nothing hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thee to pay thy vowes in due time, and deferre not vntill death to be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified. Before thou prayeſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ecclus. 18.21. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>prepare thy ſelfe, and be not as one that temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For it will not auaile a man afterwards with <hi>Balaam, to wiſh to dye the death of the Righteous;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Num. 25.10.</note> who hath not before with <hi>Iacob</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauoured to leade the life of the righteous. Therefore <hi>Iſaiah</hi> warnes vs, and ſayes, <hi>Seeke you the Lord while he may be found.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſaiah 55.6.</note> For that words be but winde, is here a true prouerbe. <hi>Not euery one</hi> (ſaith the Iudge himſelfe) <hi>that
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:5271:66"/>ſaith vnto me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 7.21.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord, Lord, ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the Kingdome of heauen, but hee that doth the will of my Father which is in heauen.</hi> Wherefore it ſeemes we may (ſooner in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian charity) feare the end of a careleſſe man, that onely calls and prayes to GOD at his laſt houre, then of a godly man, who in his extreamity (by reaſon of a burning Feauer) dyeth in a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging phrenſie.</p>
               <p>But is there no hope then of a ſinfull mans repentance to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the laſt period of his life? Yes certainly, and that out of the very words of the afore-na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Iudge. Hee doth not ſhut out all thoſe that haue not done his Fathers will, as if it were too late to doe it at the laſt houre: <hi>but thoſe onely which doe not the will of the Father which is in heauen,</hi>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:5271:66"/>pointing as with his gracious finger to this, that it is neuer too late to doe his Fathers will. And this is his will, <hi>that the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked forſake his way, and the vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous man his thoughts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſaiah. 55.7.</note> 
                  <hi>and that hee returne vnto the Lord.</hi> That is, that by earneſt repentance, hee continually ſtriue to attaine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſincere conuerſion, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in an vnfained loathing of our deparau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d nature, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of all our tranſgreſſions, and euill luſtes. And withall, an earneſt longing to be by Chriſt our onely Sauiour receiued, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, and iuſtified. And laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to haue a conſtant purpoſe, to vſe all meanes throughout the whole courſe of our life (though it yet ſhould laſt-an hundred yeares) to obſerue all occaſions for keeping Gods commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:5271:67"/>And that not for feare of that puniſhment, which ſhall befall all tranſgreſſours, but out of that meere loue and affection, which like good children wee beare vnto our heauenly Father. And then (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>Will God be mercifull vnto vs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ier. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>for with him is much forgiueneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We muſt then follow the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the valiant Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and wraſtlers in olde time, who for many dayes together before hand, cauſed their bodies to be rubbed, annointed, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed, yea tyed themſelues to a certaine ſtrict courſe of dyet, and then they preſented them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues (ſo prepared) in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Olympian games, to fight or wraſtle in open view for ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. In like manner muſt wee long afore prepare our ſoules
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:5271:67"/>couragiouſly to fight with Death at the appointed time, that when it aſſaile vs, it may not hurt vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Point.</hi> The armes or ſting of death.</note> But how may we ſecure our ſelues againſt it? By two man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of meanes. Wee muſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arme it, and arme our ſelues. We muſt diligently enquire where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall it can hurt vs, and hauing found it out, ſeeke to bereaue it thereof.</p>
               <p>The Philiſtims were ſubtill enough, to giue <hi>Sampſon</hi> no reſt, till they had vnderſtood where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his great ſtrength conſiſted. As ſoone as his Philiſtine dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling heard, that it conſiſted in his haire, ſhe preſently plaid the Barber, and cut it off. Then was <hi>Sampſon weake as another man,</hi> ſaith the Scripture.<note place="margin">Iudg. 16.17.</note> Now wherein the power of Death conſiſteth, the Apoſtle hath ſhewed to vs,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:5271:68"/>to wit, in the ſting, this is the dart wherewithall Death peirceth our ſoules.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.56.</note> And this ſting (faith he) are our ſinnes. Whoſoeuer then will deale prudently and prouidently, muſt endeauour to bereaue Death of this ſting. Not when it comes to ſtruggle with him, and when hee lyes on his death-bed, for then it ſtingeth too deepe. But hee muſt doe this before it comes to aſſaile him.</p>
               <p>The ancient Poets faigned,<note place="margin">Faith in Chriſt.</note> that <hi>Pallas</hi> the Goddeſſe of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, bore a ſhield, that turned all thoſe that gazed on it into ſtone. But wee know, that the holy Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> who was a ſeruant of the Sonne of God (the true wiſedome of his heauenly Father) hath ſhewed vs the true ſhield,<note place="margin">Eph. 6.16.</note> wherewith wee may bee able to quench all the fierie darts
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:5271:68"/>of the wicked; to wit, in truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Ieſus Chriſt. This faith then is termed, and is really the right ſhield, againſt, which the force of the helliſh ſting of death ſhall not bee able to preuaile, though it aſſaile vs with as much fury as may bee: For (to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence at the beginning) when the firſt man through infidelity, did tranſgreſſe his Creators or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, hee (with all his future Progenie) loſt the right of being termed the Sonne of God. And ſo caſt himſelfe, and vs all (who reſemble him in dayly diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience) out of Gods mercy into his eternall wrath. Wherein we ſhould alſo haue remained for euer, had not the diuine wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome otherwiſe prouided. This alone hath deuiſed a remedie, and hath ordained that the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:5271:69"/>Sonne of God (as the fitteſt perſon in Trinity) to reſtore man vnto his loſt title of a Sonne) ſhould aſſume humane nature. And this not onely that therein hee might yeeld perfect obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence vnto God, but for this end chiefly, that he might ſuffer that wrath and puniſhment which man by ſinne had deſerued, and ſo ſatisfie Gods Iuſtice for mans tranſgreſſions. All which in due time being fulfilled,<note place="margin">Ioh. 19 36.</note> ſo many are now ſtill acquitted before God as come to beleeue in him. <hi>For he that beleeueth in him, is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 3.18.</note> 
                  <hi>but he that beleeueth not, is condemned already.</hi> This Sonne of God, <hi>as a Lambe without ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh, and without ſpot hath offered vp his pretious blood vnto God for vs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.19.</note> ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peter.</hi> And thereby <hi>taketh he away the ſinne of the world,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 1.29.</note>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:5271:69"/>ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iohn,</hi> and conſequently the ſting of death;<note place="margin">2 Tim 1.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Yea death it ſelfe is aboliſhed by his appearanee,</hi> ſayes S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whoſoeuer then is thus ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with faith in his Sauiour Chriſt, how ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death or its ſting hurt him? <hi>Hee that beleeueth on the Sonne,<note place="margin">1 Ioh 3.36.</note> hath euerlaſting life,</hi> as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iohn</hi> witneſſeth. Death indeed doth retaine its force to kill our naturall fleſh with a dart, but this Shield or Buckler ſo defends our ſoule, that this dart cannot touch it. Now what a comfort is this for a dying man? that now wee may freely vſe the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>O Death where is thy ſting?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.55.57</note> 
                  <hi>O Graue where is thy victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie? But thankes be to God which giueth vs the victory, through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But many a one findes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe<note place="margin">3 <hi>Point.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:5271:70"/>but faint in faith.<note place="margin">Confirmation of weak faith.</note> How ſhall I know certainly, thinkes hee, whether I be one of thoſe, which God hath called &amp; choſen to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy his gracious promiſes, or of thoſe tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> haue nothing to doe wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h them? A man migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede here anſwere, <hi>the Lord knoweth his.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.29.</note> And he that (as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> farther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eacheth) doth cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly feele the teſtimonie of the holy Ghoſt within him,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.15.</note> may vndoubtedly aſſure himſelfe of his ſaluation. This is certaine, and he that feeles this, can haue not better in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ruction. Yet will we endeauour to ſet theſe in the way to find true Chriſtian com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, who through weakneſſe of faith, doe not feele ſuch a teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie in their ſickneſſe.</p>
               <p>Firſt then the Sauiour of the world, giues vs this certaine to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:5271:70"/>
                  <hi>He that belceueth and is bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, ſhall be ſaued:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mar. 16.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6.</note> 
                  <hi>but he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth not, ſhall be damned.</hi> Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer therefore findes himſelfe to haue beene baptized in the name of God; and beſides, hath often beene preſent at publique prayers, and preaching of the word of God, and beene inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the holy Sacrament: may already hope, that he thereby is called to the vni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erſall, or at l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t to the viſible Church of Chriſt. And whoſoeuer doth further perceiue in his heart, that Gods ſpirit hath called him to his Church, and doth beleeue that Chriſt his blood is ſufficient for the wiping out of all his ſinnes, yea doth conceiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that GOD himſelfe doth proffer him his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, if onely hee can but embrace it with ſtedfaſt faith;
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:5271:71"/>the ſame (though he cannot yet vndoubtedly beleeue it) muſt know that God hereby ſets ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation before his eyes.</p>
               <p>And if we haue further found a continuall inclination in our ſelues to heare the word of God, to obſerue his commandements: and (as we ſaid before) to a true repentance of our negligence, we may ſafely beleeue, that wee are in the way which leades to Chriſt his ſheepe-fold. For he ſayes himſelfe, <hi>My ſheepe heare my voyce,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 10.27.</note> 
                  <hi>and I know them, and they follow me.</hi> Yea, if we endeauour to imploy our ſelues in all good workes, to be obedient to Chriſt, we haue already ſome fruites of faith. And if we haue the fruits, wee muſt alſo haue the roote, though yet couered with earth, or with our earthly thoughts. For
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:5271:71"/>we muſt aſſure our ſoules, <hi>that the good Lord will,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Chro. 30.19.</note> 
                  <hi>pardon euery one that prepareth his heart to ſeeke God.</hi> As King <hi>Hezekiah</hi> prayed for thoſe Iſraelites, that did eate the paſſeouer without due purifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, according to the Law. As alſo S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> comforts and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages the Corinthians, ſaying, <hi>If there be firſt a willing minde, it is accepted according to that a man hath,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 8.12.</note> 
                  <hi>and not according to that hee hath not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides, if wee feele in our conſcience that God loues vs, we may certainly conclude out of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iohns</hi> words, that we are of thoſe, <hi>vnto whom God hath ſent his Sonne to be a propitiation for our ſinnes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 4.10.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And if beſides we finde that we loue God, we may alſo (vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Pauls</hi> word) <hi>expect the things
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:5271:72"/>which God hath prepared for them that loue him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 2.9.</note> And what is this but a token of our faith? Wee may then, yea muſt ſtill cry out, and pray with the childs father in the Goſpell:<note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r. 9.24.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord I beleeue, helpe thou mine vnbeliefe.</hi> Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly truſting, that as Ieſus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored that mans Childe to his corporall health, hee will alſo worke vpon our ſoule that cure that ſhall be effectuall, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur the ſaluation of it.</p>
               <p>And if euer wee haue felt in our prayers, (eſpecially being at deathes dore) <hi>that the Spirit did beare witneſſe with our ſpirit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.16.</note> 
                  <hi>that we were the children of God.</hi> We may freely bee confident, that this God his mercy remaines con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant towards vs. For hee ſtill continues the ſame towards them that doe not willingly for,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:5271:72"/>ſake him. Yea, though our ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conſcience do witneſſe againſt vs, that with deſire and greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, wee haue ſince that time committed many ſinnes: yet is it no ſmall comfort if ſhee can alſo witneſſe vnto vs, that after the committing thereof, we haue often caſt our ſelues downe at Gods feete, with true ſorrow and repétance. For this is indeed the fault &amp; condition of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Nor can this true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance proceede from any but from God, who is the fountaine of all good. If then he ſend vs true repentance, hee endeauours our Saluation; if hee endeauour it, he will performe it. God in his word bids vs, <hi>Comfort the feeble minded,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.14.15</note> wee may therefore well beleeue, that hee himſelfe will doe it. Let vs then (as it
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:5271:73"/>followes there) <hi>pray without ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.13.</note> 
                  <hi>and hope to the end for the grace that is to be brought vnto vs, at the Reuelation of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Comfort a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the temptation of the deuill.</note> But if any man there be that cannot perceiue or feele in his ſoule a ſtedfaſt hope, that his prayer is heard of GOD, but finds himſelfe depreſt by meanes of his riotous and vnruly life, he muſt not therefore giue himſelfe ouer to deſpaire. It is true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, that Sathan our enemie, (who aſſaults euen the holieſt minded men oft in their extrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie) hath ſufficient matter to torment this miſerable creature withall. But <hi>ſhouldeſt thou marke iniquities,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 130.3.</note> 
                  <hi>O Lord; who ſhall ſtand? But there is forgiueneſſe with thee. The Lordour God is a mercifull God.</hi> If we be ſinners,<note place="margin">Deut. 4.31.</note> wee are thoſe that Chriſt came to redeeme.
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:5271:73"/>
                  <hi>For he came not to call the righteous,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 9.12. &amp; 13.</note> 
                  <hi>but ſinners to repentance, for</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>the whole neede not the Phyſitian, but they that are ſicke.</hi> Let vs only earneſtly runne after him, Call on him by faith, as did the ſick, the blinde, the lame (as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> hath diſtinctly ſet downe) and wee may yet be cured with them. Yea rather before them, for our Sauiour came into the world to heale the ſickneſſe of the ſoule, and did but heale their bodily diſeaſes, thereby to moue them, to giue him leaue to take their ſoules in hand. And by theſe externall things he would haue vs to feele his infinite loue. <hi>Salomons</hi> words indeed befit him well, who telleth vs that <hi>Lone co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth all ſinnes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 10.12.</note> Sinne indeed is ſo ſtrong, that it did hinder man from entring into heauen, into
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:5271:74"/>which as yet hee neuer had ſet foote. But the loue of God was of farregreater might, that <hi>cauſed him to ſend his onely begotten Sonne into the world out of heauen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 4.9.</note> 
                  <hi>where he was in all glory,</hi> and that to this end, that euen the feebleſt <hi>might liue through him.</hi> This incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible loue S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> termeth, <hi>the riches of his grace.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 1.7.</note> Theſe riches then, and this infinite trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his loue, <hi>is the true wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding grament,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 22.12.</note> that will hide all our ſores <hi>at the wedding of the King,</hi> and will richly adorne all wretched and forlorne ſoules, notwithſtanding any eſtate of pouerty or miſery, that their ſin ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h brought them to, if onely they can ſit it vnto themſelues by faith.</p>
               <p>Therefore, if the deuill aſſaile vs,<note place="margin">Iam. 4.7.</note> let vs <hi>reſiſt him</hi> (ſaith the
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:5271:74"/>Apoſtle) <hi>and he will flee from vs.</hi> If hee doe obiect and teſtifie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, that we haue not with <hi>Maries</hi> zeale choſen the better part. Let vs conſtantly hope that neuertheleſſe,<note place="margin">Ioh. 11.5.</note> ſeruing Chriſt with <hi>Marthas</hi> vprightneſſe, wee may notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding be beloued of him. If he ſhall ſuggeſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, that we muſt not thinke to ſee that vnſpeakeable ioy of the third heauen, which was ſhewed <hi>Paul,</hi> to that Elect veſſell of God,<note place="margin">Luk. 23.46.</note> yet let vs conſtantly truſt, that we ſhall enioy that bliſſe in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, which was granted to the Thiefe on the Croſſe. If hee tempt vs with the text of Holy writ, <hi>that GOD doth not heare the prayers of ſinners:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mich. 3.4.</note> let vs anſwere him with Holy writ againe:<note place="margin">Math. 4.10.</note> 
                  <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from me Sathan.</hi> God ſweares by himſelfe,<note place="margin">Ezech. 33.11.</note> 
                  <hi>that hee hath no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:5271:75"/>in the death of the wicked, but that the wicked man turne from his way, and liue:</hi> yea, <hi>there is more ioy in heauen ouer one ſinner that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penteth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 15.7.</note> 
                  <hi>then ouer ninety and nine iuſt perſons, which neede no repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi> Therefore let vs turne our hearts to God,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.25.</note> 
                  <hi>hope for that we ſee not, and expect it with patience.</hi> Doe we not heare from Chriſt himſelfe that Iamentable voyce, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken mee?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 23.48.</note> Yet preſently after that, <hi>Father into thy hands I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend my ſpirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wee muſt alſo know that this our trembling for feare of Gods wrath, is a token that wee doe not with worldlings careleſly neglect our ſinnes, or ſeeke to hide them from Gods ſight. But that we feele them with <hi>Dauid, and doe confeſſe them vnto him,</hi> and
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:5271:75"/>therefore may hope with him, <hi>that the Lord forgiueth vs our tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsions.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 32.5.</note> Wee haue with the Prodigall ſerued the world and the deuill: but now in our po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty and agonie wee cry out with him: <hi>Father I haue ſinned againſt heauen and in thy ſight,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 15.20.21.</note> 
                  <hi>and am no more worthy to be called thy Sonne:</hi> wherefore wee muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that our heauenly Father <hi>will be moued with compaſsion, and receiue vs with a kiſſe.</hi> This ſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Prodigall childe, when hee ſo ſpake, knew not whether his Father would receiue him into fauour againe or not, yet hee found good ſucceſſe with it. Wherefore let vs (for whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and encouragement this is recorded) aſſuredly hope, that if we doe the like, God will like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe receiue vs. For to haue
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:5271:76"/>compaſſion on his children, is the true nature of a father, which that we may aſſure our ſelues to finde in God, our Lord Ieſus Chriſt (to our great comfort) puts this name in our mouth, in the very beginning of our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. Let vs then cry out with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ceaſing,<note place="margin">Math. 6.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Our Father forgiue vs our treſpaſſes: deliuer vs from euill,</hi> and wee doubtleſſe in him ſhall finde the right affection and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of a Father.</p>
               <p>Let vs obſerue alſo the two Diſciples, that had in a manner loſt both faith and hope, and (trauailing towards <hi>Emaus</hi>) were troubled in their ſoules concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the death of Ieſus Chriſt. who they had hoped (as they complained) ſhould haue deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Iſraell,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 24.21.</note> but now ſeemed to haue loſt that hope. And out
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:5271:76"/>of the aboundance of their heart, their mouth vttered theſe things vnto a ſtranger in the field. Now what befell them? Did the Lord reiect them, becauſe they told him this, euen to his face? No: hee tooke pitty rather on their infidelity, and was with them ere they thought on him. And ſo let vs hope beyond hope, that our Redeemer mercifully now ſtands and beholds our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity, though we ſee him not. And that he in due time, will ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry kindly and aſſuredly let vs feele his compaſſion and ayde.</p>
               <p>Yea if God ſent the Prophet <hi>Nathan,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.7.</note> to that King that pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uately by adulterie and murther, had ſinned againſt him, and if he prepared a crowing Cocke,<note place="margin">Math. 26.75.</note> for that Apoſtle that publiquely had denied him, and beheld them
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:5271:77"/>both with the eye of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, before euer they tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly perceiued their owne ſins, or euer thought of repentance. O may not we then beleeue that he will haue mercy on vs, who haue our heart harder preſt downe by our ſinnes, then if a milſtone lay on it, and lie now ſighing, to be releaſt? Yea, we muſt beleeue it, when the Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of the world himſelfe ſaith it. Behold, hee is ſo mercifull vnto thoſe, whoſe hearts are ſore oppreſt with the burthen of their ſinnes, that he doth not ſtay till they finde him. But hee ſeekes them, and cries out himſelfe with a loude voyce, <hi>Come vnto me all yee that labour and are heauie laden.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 11.28.</note> To what end? to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe them, no certainly. <hi>I will giue you reſt,</hi> ſaith he: Let a man
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:5271:77"/>obſerue this well, and ruminate priuately on it, and his heart ſhall be forced, to powre out ſecretly before the Lord either theſe or the like words.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A comfortable meditation.</note> 
                  <hi>O Lord Ieſu,</hi> Almighty God the onely Sauiour of the world, doeſt thou call mee? wilt thou refreſh me? Thou, thy ſelfe, in whoſe power onely the ſauing and condemning of my ſoule doth conſiſt? Doeſt thou pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe me this, who art truth it ſelfe? and that becauſe I finde my ſelfe loaden wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h many ſins? <hi>O Lord,</hi> what, or whom neede I then to feare? I come, I come, I am he whom thou calleſt. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, I come bur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hened and ſo ouer-laden wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h all my ſinnes, that I cannot appeare before thee ſtanding vpright, but fall downe at thy foote. Thou
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:5271:78"/>onely O Lord refreſh, refreſh mee: yea Lord, I am confident that thou wilt. Thy word is thy deede: yea thou doeſt it already, and I feele it. My ſoule is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued and refreſhed with a reſt, with a peace that ſurpaſſeth all the worlds treaſure. <hi>And thy Spirit beareth witneſſe with my Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.16.</note> euen in this my greateſt affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, <hi>that I am one of thy children.</hi> Therefore doe I moſt thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay; Bleſſed be thy name for euer and euer.</p>
               <p>He that meditates hereon,<note place="margin">4 <hi>Point.</hi> A longing for death.</note> and (as he ought) comforts himſelfe with the ſame, may not he freely ſay with <hi>Simon, Lord now letteſt thou thy ſeruant depart in peace:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 2.29.</note> 
                  <hi>for mine eyes haue ſeene thy ſaluation:</hi> May he not ſing with <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord is my light and my ſaluation, whom ſhall I feare, the Lord is the
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:5271:78"/>ſtrength of my life, of whom ſhall I be afraide?</hi> And ſo conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proceede to the end of that comfortable Pſalme, applying the ſame to himſelfe againſt all his Spirituall temptations. May hee not with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> be aſſured, <hi>that neither death, nor life,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.38.</note> 
                  <hi>nor An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, nor principalities, nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature ſhall be able to ſeperate him from the loue of GOD, which is in Chriſt Ieſus our Lord.</hi> Yea he will reioyce, that he may follow his Lord, euen at the heeles paſſing through the ſame dore of death, which hee went through before him. And will willingly, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting light by this life, and all what ſo euer hee hath in the world, crie out with <hi>Salomon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccles. 7.1.</note> 
                  <hi>the day of death is better then the day of
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:5271:79"/>birth,</hi> becauſe it is a meanes to bring him vnto an vnexpreſſable ioy, which will then eſpecially quicken his heart, when he ſhall conſider what entertainment hee is then and there to expect.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The place of the ſoule.</note> If now wee enquire of the place of the bleſſed ſoules, wee know that heauen is made ouer to them by promiſe. Not the ayre that the cloudes and fowles houer in,<note place="margin">Math. 5.3.4. &amp; 26.26.</note> which ſometimes is called heauen. This is too nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and ſubiect to dayly cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption: nor that heauen neither or firmament that the ſtarres gliſter in, though it be ſomewhat more ſpacious and more perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent. For euen this alſo at the laſt day ſhall be ſhaken, <hi>and the ſtarres ſhall fall downe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 24.29.</note> It is a farre other thing that God hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided for his Elect. It is the
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:5271:79"/>third heauen which that choſen veſſell <hi>Paul</hi> was caught vp into.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.2.</note> It is the vppermoſt heauen <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsing all the heauens,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 4.10.</note> whither Chriſt is aſcended,<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.2.</note> 
                  <hi>where is roome enough for many manſions.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 14.3.</note> This is ſtedfaſt and permanent vnto all eternity.<note place="margin">Wiſ. 3.1.</note> Hither Chriſt hath promiſed to take all his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers vnto him,<note place="margin">Luk. 23.43.</note> 
                  <hi>that they may bee where he is.</hi> There be the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſoules in the hand of God. There is the penitent Thiefe in <hi>Paradiſe.</hi> There is <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus in Abrahams boſome.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 16.23.</note> There S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſawe <hi>them that were mark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 7.9.</note> 
                  <hi>before the Throne and before the Lambe.</hi> One onely place, ſet foorth by diuers names. What a glorious comfort then is this for vs, that our ſoule, as ſoone as ſhee forſakes this earth, ſhall bee receiued into
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:5271:80"/>ſo ſtately an habitation?</p>
               <p>Concerning a mid way man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or fiery priſon, which ſome haue endeauoured to ſettle, by the way, there to purge and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie the bleſſed ſoules, ſome cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine yeares before their aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into heauen, wee finde no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all in holy writ thereof ſet downe, nor yet declared by the examples of any Saints de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed. For euen as in this life, there are but two kindes of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſations ſet before vs, <hi>to walke in light or darkneſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> but two wayes <hi>through the narrowe, or the wide gate,</hi> ſo we read in the future life, but of two hands of God,<note place="margin">Math. 7.13.</note> 
                  <hi>the right and the left,</hi> but of two kinde of men comprehended vnder the name of <hi>ſheepe and goates;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 25.32.</note> and by conſequence then, but of two places <hi>heauen and hell.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:5271:80"/>when we are dying, let vs fixe firmely the eyes of ſaith, <hi>on the blood of Ieſus Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 1.7.</note> which (as his beloued Diſciple ſpeakes) <hi>cleanſeth vs from all ſinnes,</hi> and we ſhall directly aſcend to that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,<note place="margin">Act. 7.56.</note> which the firſt Martyr <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen,</hi> euen when hee was yet on earth, ſawe opened vnto him.</p>
               <p>On what maner our ſoules get thither, we may obſerue by the fore-named <hi>Lazarus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 16.22.</note> who was carried thither by the miniſtrie of Angels.<note place="margin">Reu. 7.10.</note> To S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iohn</hi> it is alſo reuealed what they doe there, to wit, that they praiſe God, hee ſaith farther,<note place="margin">Reu. 14.13.</note> 
                  <hi>that they reſt from their labours,</hi> that is as well from the paines and diſeaſes of the body, which ſickneſſe did here bring on them, and the troubles wherewith the wicked did op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe them, as from the labour
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:5271:81"/>and continuall warfare, which they had againſt their owne concupiſcences. Concerning which, the booke of Wiſedome ſayes very well,<note place="margin">Sap. 9.3.</note> 
                  <hi>that they are at peace.</hi> And principally at con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall peace with God, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from that trouble of minde, whereby they feared to fall into Gods wrath. And are not infinitely ſaid to reſt vnder an Altar, in reſpect of Chriſt his onely ſacrifice,<note place="margin">Reu. 6.9.</note> whereby our ſoules are reconciled vnto God.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ornaments of heauen.</note> As for the glory of this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly place, no man can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it. Yet whoſoeuer doth but obſerue how glorious, how comely God hath created this world, which is but a temporall habitation as well of the wicked as of the good, and what diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of delights he hath prepared
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:5271:81"/>for all kinde of men in the ſame, he may in ſome ſort gueſſe, how louely, how comely, how full of pleaſure that place muſt needs be, which hee hath prepared to bee an habitation for his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, whom hee hath elected to eternall bliſſe, before the foundation of the world. Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> when he faine would reueale ſome part thereof vnto vs, writes that hee ſaw a Citie,<note place="margin">Reu. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>A holy Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem of pure gold, whoſe walls were of Iaſper ſtone, and her foundations of moſt precious ſtone,</hi> things that we here chiefely eſteeme of, and yet not to bee gotten in ſuch quantity, that thereof wee may build the leaſt part of a Citie. And yet all this is nothing in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the incomprehenſible excellencie of this heauenly manſion.</p>
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:5271:82"/>
               <p>Diuine <hi>Paul</hi> had a taſt of this heauenly ioy, but hee could not finde any termes wherewith to expreſſe the ſame. But could onely ſay,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Eye hath not ſeene, eare hath not heard, neither haue there entred into the heart of man, the things which God hath prepared for them that loue him.</hi> And to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue and enioy this glory, there is no other way, but by death. Death onely fetches vs, and brings vs thither.</p>
               <p>Now as a young Prince li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſome-where in baniſhment, would exceedingly reioyce to ſee a meſſenger, ſent by the King his father to fetch him home, and to ſet him on his Throne. Euen ſo ought a childe of God, to reioyce when God ſends vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him his Meſſenger Death, to fetch him vnto his eternall king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:5271:82"/>Yea, ſo much the more then ſuch a Prince, by how much the more the Kingdome of heauen doth excell all the Kingdomes of the world: <hi>For it is better to be one day in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace of heauen</hi> (ſayes <hi>Dauid</hi>) <hi>then elſe-where a thouſand.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal 84.11.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Priuiledge of the life to come.</note> For what haue we on the face of the earth, that ſhould make vs deſire to ſtay here? If we giue ouer this life, which is but tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, and full of miſerie and trouble, wee obtaine a life on high, <hi>where there ſhall be no more death, neither ſorrow, nor crying,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reu. 21.4.</note> 
                  <hi>neither ſhall there be any more paine.</hi> If heere wee depart from our earthly parents, we are entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned there of <hi>our heauenly Father.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 5.45.</note> If heere wee leaue our chiefeſt friends and kindred, wee meete there with our brethren in
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:5271:83"/>Chriſt, <hi>cloathed in long white gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reu. 7.9.</note> If heere wee looſe our Gardens and faire Pallaces, wee finde our ſelues there in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, where the tree of life is continually growing. If heere we remoue out of a famous Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, wee become there Citizens of <hi>the heauenly Ieruſalem.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 12.22.</note> Or if here we forgoe our Princely ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, there we are named <hi>chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the moſt high.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 6.35.</note> Yea, if here we forſake euen an earthly Kingdome, we poſſeſſe there <hi>a heauenly Kingdome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 1.33.</note> 
                  <hi>whereof there ſhall be no end.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſeeing of God.</note> When further wee proceede and conſider, that we are promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed there to ſee God, <hi>and that we ſhall ſee him as he is,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 5.8.</note> how can wee but hope to ſee the holy Trinity with full ſatisfaction?<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Wee ſhall ſee him in whoſe preſence is the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:5271:83"/>of ioy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 16.11.</note> and who ſhall ſay then vnto vs, <hi>Enter into thy maſters ioy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 25.21.</note> O what an vnexpreſſable ioy will this bee? What can our mindes imagine, or hearts wiſh more!</p>
               <p>If the Queene of <hi>Seba</hi> cryed out, that thoſe men were happy <hi>which ſtoode before Salomon to heare his wiſedome;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Reg. 10.8.</note> how happy will thoſe be, that ſhall ſtand before Ieſus, who is the wiſedome of his heauenly Father? And if <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt leaped for very ioy at the preſence of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Luk. 1.44.</note> while he was yet in his mothers wombe: And <hi>Simeon</hi> was ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied when hee had but ſeene the childe in the Temple,<note place="margin">Luk. 2.30.</note> what ioy and ſatiety will thoſe receiue, that ſhall ſee him ſit at the right hand of his Father, in eternall glory?</p>
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:5271:84"/>
               <p>The three Apoſtles of our Lord, when they had but a very ſmall reſemblance therof in that ſhort transfiguration of Chriſt, how ſoone did they forget &amp; ſet light by the world, with all her appurtenances, &amp; cried out, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter it is good for vs to be here,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 9.33.</note> 
                  <hi>and let vs heere build vs tabernacles:</hi> What doe thoſe Apoſtles now feele? Or what doe they ſay now, with all thoſe that perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly behold his glory, and dwell in it?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The honour of our ſoules.</note> When we farther yet conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that we our ſelues ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine there <hi>the Crowne of glory,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.4.</note> 
                  <hi>that fadeth not away,</hi> as <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeakes: And that Gods children (being by Chriſt iuſtified <hi>ſhall ſhine forth as the Sunne in the Kingdome of their Father,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3.43.</note> 
                  <hi>and be as the Angels of God in heauen;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 22.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.</note> 
                  <hi>yea, are there to
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:5271:84"/>raigne for euer and euer:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reu. 22.5.</note> What heart, what ſoule can chuſe, but long exceedingly to forgoe this world, and to attaine to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God? <hi>Dauid</hi> cries out, <hi>As the Hart panteth after the water brookes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 42.1.</note> 
                  <hi>ſo panteth my ſoule after thee, O God. My ſoule thirſteth for God, for the liuing God, when ſhall I come and appeare before God?</hi> Now that which he longed for, euery true beleeuer, after this life once ended, ſhall for euer enjoy.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The meeting of the body and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ule to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</note> But whoſoeuer farther will caſt his eyes, on the generall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the dead may finde yet farther matter of ioy and comfort. Euery one may in ſome ſort conceiue, how vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeably theſe two old friends ſoule and body will reioyce, when (after many ages) they ſhall meete againe, and perceiue
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:5271:85"/>that each of them is in a happy eſtate.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.45.</note> But chiefly, <hi>when this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible ſhall haue put on incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and this mortall ſhall haue put on immortality,</hi> and bee partaker with the ſoule of heauenly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light. Yea the Lord Ieſus, <hi>ſhall change our vile body, that it may be faſhioned like vnto his glorious body.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 3.21.</note> What is there in heauen, or in earth more excellent? or what can bee imagined that deſerues rather to be deſired?</p>
               <p>Yea, with our corporall eyes, we ſhall behold Chriſt. This it was, euen this (I ſay) was it wherewith <hi>Iob</hi> comforted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in his long continued mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie, and which did releeue him in his greateſt agony. <hi>I know,</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>that my Redeemer liueth, and that hee ſhall ſtand at the latter day vpon earth: and though after
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:5271:85"/>my skinne wormes deſtroy this body, yet in my fleſh ſhall I ſee God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob 19.26.</note> 
                  <hi>who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> I ſhall ſee for my ſelfe, and mine eyes ſhall behold and not another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Stephen</hi> the Martyr had aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance hereof in this life, for hee being <hi>full of the holy Ghoſt</hi> (ſayes the Scripture) <hi>looked vp ſtedfaſtly into heauen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 7.55.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſawe the glory of God, and Ieſus ſtanding on the right hand of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With this fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t Martyr of Chriſt, let vs then co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually caſt our harts &amp; eies of faith towards heauen, and fixe them wholly on Chriſt, crying out with him, <hi>Lord Ieſus receiue my ſpirit.</hi> Yea, when wee can neither crie, nor ſpeake any more, Let vs all with <hi>Hanna,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 1.15.</note> 
                  <hi>powre out our ſoules before him,</hi> And the <hi>Spirit will make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſsion for vs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.26.</note> 
                  <hi>with groaning which cannot be vttered,</hi> and wee
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:5271:86"/>doubtleſſe with the afore-ſaid <hi>Stephen ſhall ſee heauen open, and when our time comes with him, dye in the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet if it ſhall pleaſe God, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all our good preparation,<note place="margin">An appendix.</note> to lift vs, (as he did the fore-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned <hi>Ezechias</hi>) from our b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d againe, and to reſtore vs to health, let vs take good heede that we doe not neglect likewiſe with the ſame King,<note place="margin">Eſ. 38.20.</note> 
                  <hi>to ſing ſongs in the houſe of the Lord all the dayes of our life,</hi> that is, euermore to be thankfull vnto him, to ſerue him, and to praiſe him. So the diſeaſed perſon whom Ieſus had healed at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> was preſently found in the Temple.<note place="margin">Ioh. 5.14.</note> The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Dauid</hi> teacheth vs in his hundred and ſixteenth Pſalme, that being releaſed, we ſhould <hi>call vpon him as long as we liue, walke
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:5271:86"/>before him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 116.</note> 
                  <hi>and pay our vowes vnto him in the preſence of all his people<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> which Pſalme throughout ought then to be our meditation, and our practiſe. For wee doe neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect this, and forgetting God and all godlineſſe, returne againe to our euill wayes, wee muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect ſome greater puniſhment. This the Lord demonſtrates vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs in his words to the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named diſeaſed perſon. To whom (becauſe wee ſhould not thinke it ſufficient ſometimes to appeare in the Temple) hee ſaid, <hi>Sinne no more, leſt a worſe thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall thee.</hi> That is, worſe then the ſickneſſe of eight and thirty yeares continuance, which hee had endured before. Behold how ſorely he is threatned, that after his releaſe, vngratefully ruſhes againe into his former
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:5271:87"/>ſinne. God graunt vs a better heart.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Finall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.</note> To conclude all that hath beene ſaid, as we in the firſt part haue ſhewed, that the death of the body is not hurtfull to man, and in that reſpect ought not to be fearefull: ſo we ſuppoſe, that in this ſecond part wee haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by what meanes we may make the ſame to be very profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vnto vs, and haue ſhewed in the firſt place, how that wee muſt ſettle our houſe by a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent ordering of our goods, that we ought to inure our body to a patient ſuffering of paine, and that we muſt prepare our ſoules, by a timely preparation to meet death couragiouſly. After that, we haue taught how we ought to diſarme it, and ſo to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then our ſelues (through Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:5271:87"/>faith) that its ſting may not pricke our ſoule, and bring it to the ſecond death. And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, we haue endeauoured to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh the wauering ſoule in this faith, and to relieue the troubled conſciences with comfortable ſpeeches, and examples that may inſtruct them. And laſtly, wee haue made it apparent, that death openeth a dore for our ſoule, to a life truly happy, which ſhee ſhall receiue with all aduantage, honour, and perfect ioy from her Sauiour in heauen, and ſhall poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe vnto all eternity. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we iuſtly conclude, that all Chriſtian ſoules haue great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to waxe weary of this tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, troubleſome, and ſinfull life, and earneſtly to ſay with the holy Apoſtle, <hi>Wee deſire rather to remoue out of the body,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>and be with
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:5271:88"/>Chriſt.</hi> Let vs then lift vp our ſoules to him, and heartily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate him, that he would come quickly: Yea <hi>Lord Ieſu come. The grace of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt be with vs all,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reu. 22.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="157" facs="tcp:5271:88"/>
            <head>A SHORT PRAYER CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CEIVED BY THE Author, for his Seruant that lay a dying. <hi>An.</hi> 1623.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Almighty God and moſt mercifull Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that haſt crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and by thy wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome doeſt preſerue and gouerne all things, we poore ſinners proſtrate our ſelues at thy feete, to powre out our Prayers for a ſicke creature, whom it hath pleaſed thee to
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:5271:89"/>caſt into the ſnares of death. But in doing thus our owne vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe, repreſenteth it ſelfe to our eyes. What are we, that we ſhould dare to entreate for one, who in thy ſight, (it may be) is holier and better then wee our ſelues are, and we conſequently haue more neede, that ſome other ſhould pray for vs. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, O wiſe and moſt mercifull Lord, ſeeing that thou haſt commanded vs for to pray one for an other, ſanctifie (wee pray thee) our heart, and guide our tongue, that our weake prayers may be acceptable vnto thee. Whereby wee deſire of thee, that thou wouldeſt fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably behold, this our brother lying in great diſtreſſe. Doe not behold in him that corruption, which as well by originall ſinne,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:5271:89"/>as by dayly tranſgreſſion hee is fallen into. But (O Lord) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard him as thy creature, and as the worke of thine owne hands. Caſt not thine eyes on his owne deformity, but on the worke of thy mercy, whereby thou haſt renewed thine image in him. Forgiue vs, forgiue him all his ſinnes and tranſgreſſions, for his names ſake, whom thou haſt mercifully appointed to bee a ranſome for vs; before the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the world, and reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in due time, to wit, Ieſus Chriſt, who deſcended from heauen to take on him mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and in the ſame to ſuffer for vs, and by ſuffering to ſaue thoſe, that beleeue in him. Grant him, O Father, and grant each of vs, to bee of that little flocke, which through his merrits is
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:5271:90"/>elected to ſaluation. Strengthen him in faith, that he, as a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Chriſt may aſſure him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe that he is partaker of all his merits. We entreat thee for our ſelues: we entreat thee for him as our brother in Chriſt, and eſpeciall for him, as one to whom our lone is confirmed by a long continuance of dwelling and liuing together. O Lord, we pray for him as for our owne ſoule. Be mercifull vnto him. Let him taſt of thy meekeneſſe. Let him feele in his ſoule, that thou haſt quitted him of all his ſinnes, and turned thy wrath from him. Strengthen him in body ſtrengthen him in ſoule. Shew thy power in this wealie fleſh of his. Touch his tongue, that he may call on thee, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his good hope, euen in
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:5271:90"/>this his greateſt frailty. Or at the leaſt, O God, ſo infuſe thy diuine light into his Spirit, that it may driue away all dazeling and darkneſſe from him. Turne away from him all diſtruſt, and diſtreſſe of minde. O Lord be mercifull vnto him: And by this example teach vs wiſdome, that we in our greateſt proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, may flye all vaine arrogan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, beholding here what a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der worme man is, when thou doeſt but viſite him with ſicknes. But at this preſent, O Father, comfort him that feeles this by experience. Strengthen him, and mercifully receiue him into thy protection. Shield him from the arrowes of that wicked one, that ſtill is wandring about, but chiefely aſſaulting vs in our greateſt extreamity. Set him
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:5271:91"/>free, O Lord, and if it ſeeme good vnto thee, reſtore vnto him his former health. If not, ſend thine Angels vnto him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat they in due time may bring his ſoule into thy boſome. Let him with <hi>Stephen,</hi> if not with bodily eyes, yet with the eyes of faith, ſee his Sauiour ſtanding in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, euen ready to receiue his ſoule. This we deſire, this we begge of thee, O Lord, for thy Sonne, our Sauiours ſake, euen in that prayer which he hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited for vs, and begunne with that comfortable word <hi>Our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our Father that art in heauen,</hi> heare vs whom thou haſt vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed to name thy children. <hi>Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed,</hi> among vs, <hi>be thy Name. Thy Kingdome come. Thy will be done on earth as it is in heauen,</hi> euen
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:5271:91"/>in this our weakeſt brother. <hi>Giue vs this day our dayly bread,</hi> not that of our body onely, but the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall and neceſſary foode alſo of our ſoules. Forgiue him, and <hi>forgiue vs our treſpaſſes, as wee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue them that treſpaſſe againſt vs. Lead vs not into temptation:</hi> take compaſſion on our weakeneſſe, that hardly can reſiſt any thing. <hi>But deliuer vs all from euill. For thine</hi> onely, O Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>is the Kingdome, the power, and the glory, for euer and euer, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="164" facs="tcp:5271:92"/>
            <head>A Conſolation or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie againſt the Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that may befall vs by the deceaſe of our friends.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a commendable cuſtome, that after any buriall, the neereſt friends returne to the Funerall houſe, to comfort thoſe that ſuruiue. Wee in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner (hauing giuen ſome admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to the departing, would faine heere miniſter ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to the liuing. Not that we can imitate thoſe prouident comforters, who (like Spirituall
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:5271:92"/>Phyſitians) firſt diligently feele the pulſe of their Patient, and as by it they diſcerne and finde the diſeaſe, preſcribe accordingly ſome remedies: for we know no mans diſeaſe in particular. But wee will onely endeauour (as faithfull Apothecaries) to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare ſome good matter; out of the which, the afflicted may chuſe what they ſuppoſe moſt needfull for themſelues.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Lamentation ouer the dead.</note> Firſt then I ſay, that it is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnſeemely, nor vngodly, to be ſorrowfull at any ones de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, and to lament for the ſame. Wee haue the examples of our Fore-fathers.<note place="margin">Gen. 23.2.</note> 
               <hi>Abraham mourned for Sarah, and wept for her. Iacob put on ſackcloath,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 37.35.</note> 
               <hi>and mourned for his ſonne many dayes,</hi> when hee ſuppoſed his <hi>Ioſeph</hi> had beene dead.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 2.32.</note> 
               <hi>King Dauid and all the
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:5271:93"/>people wept at the Graue of Abner.</hi> Yea, <hi>Iſraell</hi> penned mournfull Ditties,<note place="margin">2 Chro. 35.25.</note> 
               <hi>at the death of their Kings,</hi> And among the firſt Chriſtians, <hi>the deuout men made great lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the death of Stephen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 1.2.</note> Euen the Sonne of God (whether the death of <hi>Lazarus</hi> moued him,<note place="margin">Ioh. 11.35.</note> or rather his ſiſters ſorrowes) wept with the weeping.<note place="margin">Rom. 2.15.</note> Wee reade likewiſe,<note place="margin">Num. 20.29.</note> that the lamenting for <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> laſted each of them <hi>thirty dayes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 34.8.</note> On the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balming of <hi>Iacob, they beſlowed fourty dayes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 50.3.</note> Yea, the Egyptians <hi>mourned threeſcore and tenne dayes.</hi> And very fitly doth a man take the time of certaine day<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, to eaſe his heart of the burthen of griefe, it ſurchargeth it by la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting and weeping. For this diſeaſe hauing ſo paſſed the worſt, is then the eaſier to be
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:5271:93"/>cured. The ſorrowfull finding himſelfe wearied out, by ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long mourning, giues way the more willingly to comfort. Which indeed ought not in due time be neglected, but willingly accepted. For, though the firſt gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>efe be not condemnable, yet is the continuance thereof hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. <hi>For of heauineſſe commeth death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ecclus 38.18.</note> 
               <hi>and the heauineſſe of the heart breaketh ſtrength,</hi> ſayes Ieſus <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rachs</hi> ſonne.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Remedies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſorrow.</note> The Remedies to bee vſed againſt this, are either externall, or internall. The externall are foure-fold. To wit, a new ioy, as <hi>Iſaac</hi> (after the death of his mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her) conceiued at the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt approaching of his bride <hi>Rebecca.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 24.64.</note> Or otherwiſe greater vnexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted ſorrowes, as when a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man doth lament the deceaſe of
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:5271:94"/>a childe, and preſently after is bereaued of her dearely beloued husband. Where neither of theſe two fall out, there at laſt is all ſorrow by time it ſelfe at length conſumed, or at the laſt vndoubtedly by death, which is a ſure Phyſitian for all diſeaſes. But theſe things are not within our power or reach.</p>
            <p>And therefore the internall remedies are moſt profitable for vs, which are two-fold: to wit, humane reaſon, and the word of God. The one teacheth vs, not to be amazed at the loſſe of any kinde of thing, which we knew could bee taken from vs at any time. The other witneſſes vnto vs, that we ſay dayly, and ought to ſay contentedly, <hi>Our Father thy will be done.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 6.10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This will of our heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:5271:94"/>(if ſo be we be his children) muſt bee the guide and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of all our affections. Wee muſt conſider, that whatſoeuer pleaſes him, is beſt for his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens welfare. He hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for each one his Mare in wedlocke, his louing Parents, his deare children, his comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able friends, his truſty ſeruants, and hath linked them in loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. But when? when hee knew that it was needfull for them. For how long time? for ſo long as it was conuenient for them both. And he that hath created all, continueth Lord of all: Hee giueth not his right to man, euen in the ſmalleſt crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: Hee doth but lend vs one to another. Whenſoeuer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee ſhall demand his owne, whether it bee wife, childe, or
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:5271:95"/>friend, wee ought (as to the owner) willingly to ſurrender it vnto him againe.</p>
            <p>And if we haue on them ſo ſet our affection (which ought to be limited by Gods appoin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed time) as to things perpetually to continue, wee ought to lament, not any mans departure, but our owne miſreckoning. Doe wee not know that Gods verdict, <hi>Duſt thou art,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>and vnto duſt thou ſhalt returne,</hi> muſt ſtand firme, and be made good vpon <hi>Adam</hi> and all his poſterity?</p>
            <p>If any body ſhould take great delight in the greene boughes, and flouriſhing fruit of his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard, would wee not eſteeme him a very ſimple and ſilly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, if he ſhould vexe, and pine away for griefe, when the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters froſt came and deſtroyed
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:5271:95"/>them? How then can hee be deemed very wiſe, that troubles himſelfe when he ſees this earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fleſh, which (as the Prophet cries out) <hi>is all but graſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 40.6.</note> to wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther away. This is the only dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, of the Winters froſt the certaine time is knowne, where of Deathes approach the certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is well knowne, but not the time. When it pleaſeth GOD but to call, and ſay, <hi>Returne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 90.3.</note> we muſt on, and finiſh our courſe in this world.</p>
            <p>Wee then that heare and ſee this, and alſo know, that (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the body wither) yet the ſoule of the faithfull enters into eternall bliſſe, ought to take heede we <hi>ſorrow not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.13.</note> 
               <hi>euen as others doe, which haue no hope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But conſidering that we haue (beſide this wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted ſorrow)
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:5271:96"/>many other particular occaſions alſo of griefe and ſorrow, and that euery one doth iudge his owne the greateſt, we will in briefe touch ſome of them, and endeauour withall to finde out ſome ſpecial remedies for them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eſpeciall occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</note> The occaſion then of our mourning is two-fold, to wit, either in reſpect of the deceaſed, or in reſpect of our ſelues.</p>
            <p>In reſpect of the deceaſed we ſorrow for three reaſons: either becauſe hee dyed in his child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, or becauſe hee was taken away, and brought vnto his end by ſome miſchance, or thirdly, becauſe we feare he dyed in his ſinnes.</p>
            <p>That which reſpecteth our ſelues, hath alſo three reaſons. To wit, either becauſe his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany was deare vnto vs: Or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:5271:96"/>his helpe was very neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary vnto vs: Or laſtly, becauſe we had not ſufficiently reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led our ſelues vnto him.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Occaſion.</hi>
               </note> wee bewaile our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, as fruites not yet ripe, too ſoone plucked from the tree, as though this did not agree with Gods ordinance. Yet we know that our Gardners doe not ſet all plants, to the intent they ſhould all bring their fruites to maturi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, neither is it fitting they ſhould ſo doe. They let the Muſtard and the Fennell ſtalke produce and nouriſh their ſeede to ripeneſſe. But they doe not ſuffer the Roſe-buſh, nor Gilly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flower ſtockes, nor many more, to bring their fruit or ſeede to maturity, but gather their flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, as ſoone as they be blowne. A childe likewiſe doth meruaile
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:5271:97"/>to ſee the Father gather Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuts or Figges, before they bee growne to their full bigne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e. But the Comfit-maker or Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecarie that comfites them, knowes that they ſerue b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tter for his vſe, then if they were bigger or riper. We ought then willingly to yeeld to the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of all things, the like free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and choiſe. He knoweth whom he hath ordained to olde age, and whom not. He knowes what fruit would ſooner rot, then ripen, if hee ſhould not plucke it off betimes, that is, who rather with the multitude, <hi>would enter at the wide gate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 7.13.</note> then with the ſmall company <hi>at the ſtraight.</hi> Yea, wee muſt thinke that many in their thought,<note place="margin">Wiſd. 4.11.</note> 
               <hi>are ſpeedily taken away, leſt that wickedneſſe ſhould al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their vnderſtanding: Or deceit
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:5271:97"/>beguile their ſoule.</hi> And who ſhould grudge then that they eſcape ſuch, either danger, or ſorrow? If the Sauiour of the world ſaith,<note place="margin">Mark. 10.13.</note> 
               <hi>Suffer little children to come vnto me,</hi> ſhall we deſire to delay them, and ſtay them here certaine yeares,<note place="margin">Luk. 15.18.</note> 
               <hi>to try their Oxen, and view the Land which they ſhould poſſeſſe?</hi> No certainly, though h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re they were euen borne to a Kingdome; for, all the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and honours thereof, the wiſeſt of Kings hath termed, but <hi>Vanity of vanities.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 1.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore as thoſe of the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar ſort reioyce, when their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren (after long ſeruice) are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced vnto ſome preferment in the Princes Court; Euen ſo may we, with more reaſon, r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ioyce, that our heauenly King hath eſteemed ours worthy to take
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:5271:98"/>them vnto him, euen before they haue done him any ſeruice at all. Therefore let vs caſt off our mourning with <hi>Dauid,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (according to his Prophecie) <hi>I ſhall goe to him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.23.</note> 
               <hi>but hee ſhall not come to me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But my honeſt brother (may ſome one ſay) is careleſly neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, or pittifully murthered. Let thoſe bewaile this, that were the occaſion thereof. But as for him, ſeeing that the diuine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence hath a hand therein, hee ſuffers thereby no harme. He is got whether he intended, &amp; that not through many by-lanes, but euen the very neereſt way.</p>
            <p>If two Sea-faring men,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Occaſion.</hi>
               </note> ſhould ayme at one Port, and the one by reaſon of a Calme, ſhould lye lingering by the way, and the other by a Storme ſhould bee
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:5271:98"/>violently caught, and ſo caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Hauen. Doe you thinke, that this man would wiſh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe againe with the other in the Calme? The Storme may bee ſomewhat troubleſome vnto him; yet now he reioyceth, that by meanes thereof, he is attained vnto his wiſhed Port. And the like muſt we thinke concerning our brother, who we ſuppoſe is bereaued of life by ſome miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance. Eſpecially conſidering that theſe vnexpected iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, may not be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med any ſigne of Gods eſpeciall wrath: for <hi>thoſe vpon whom the Tower of Silao fell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 13.4.</note> 
               <hi>were not ſinners aboue other men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea whoſoeuer dieth in the Lord,<note place="margin">Gen. 8.4. Acts 7.10.</note> though he were murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with <hi>Abel in a by-way: or ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with Stephen in the open ſtreetes,</hi>
               <pb n="178" facs="tcp:5271:99"/>the holy Ghoſt termes him bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.<note place="margin">Reu. 14.13.</note> So that this ſorrow alſo muſt be remoued, and receiue comfort.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3 <hi>Occaſion.</hi>
               </note> Whoſoeuer (thirdly) doth bewaile his neighbour, that is drowned in his drunkenneſſe, or in any other ſinne, and ſo died in Gods indignation, hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede no ſmall reaſon ſo to doe. But whether it bee conuenient for one in ſuch caſe, to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loade his ſoule with continuall mourning,<note place="margin">Ecclus 38.22.</note> that <hi>doth no way helpe the deceaſed, but hurt himſelfe,</hi> that is duly to be conſidered. And he that conſidereth it well, ſhall finde but ſmall reaſon ſo to doe. For if ſo be the par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y were who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly giuen ouer to wickedneſſe, it may be God hath ſnatcht him away,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.6</note> 
               <hi>for our example,</hi> and <hi>for his beſt aduantage;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 23.32.</note> becauſe he ſhould
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:5271:99"/>not fill full the meaſure of his wicked predeceſſours, and ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe Gods wrath againſt him. The beſt then that wee can doe for him, is, that wee endeauour to appeaſe by all manner of meanes, all thoſe which he may haue wronged, to the end that at the leaſt we may leſſen the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe that may accuſe him before God, as much as lyeth in vs.</p>
            <p>But let vs alſo looke to our ſelues, that we doe not ſtep too farre, ſpeaking of him, as if hee were certainly now caſt off from God.<note place="margin">Math. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Iudge not</hi> (ſaith the Iudge himſelfe) <hi>leſt yee be iudged.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Bridge and flood (ſayes S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) may hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent that intends to drown him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Chriſtian loue muſt cauſe vs to hope, that euen before his
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:5271:100"/>laſt gaſpe, at leaſt, he cries out, <hi>Lord remember me when thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt into thy Kingdome.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 23.45.</note> And thus hoping there ſhall be no iuſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of a continuall lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
            <p>An other (it may be) will vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſantly bewaile his betrothed bed-fellow,<note place="margin">4 <hi>Occaſion.</hi>
               </note> and ſuppoſe he does it with great reaſon. For where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as many are ſorrowfull for the death of ſome friends, or neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, he bewailes (may he ſay) <hi>the bone of his bone, and fleſh of his fleſh.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 2.23.</note> Whoſe deceaſe as he prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally feeles himſelfe, ſo hee may principally, and that with good reaſon lament it.</p>
            <p>This coniunction of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in married perſons, is indeed certainly ſuch; for man and wife according to Gods word, <hi>are one fleſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 2.24.</note> to witte, ſo long
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:5271:100"/>as both parties remaine aliue: But if <hi>the husband or wife be dead</hi> (the Apoſtle ſayes) <hi>the ſuruiuer is free to be married to another.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7.3.</note> And then this band or firſt connexion is looſed.</p>
            <p>The husband may moreouer alledge out of holy writ, that his wife <hi>was the onely Lamb,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.3.</note> 
               <hi>which lay in his boſome, and was vnto him as a daughter.</hi> And that hee for that reaſon (according to duty) <hi>loued her as his owne body,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5.28.</note> &amp; hence alſo is the more vrged to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile her.</p>
            <p>We cannot indeede but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that a good wife is a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and delight vnto vs in this life, but ſhe is not onely granted vs to this intent by God, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to be <hi>a helper vnto vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 2 18.</note> in all accidents and neceſſities of our age. And wee are commanded
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:5271:101"/>
               <hi>to dwell with her according to know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.7.</note> 
               <hi>as being heires together of the grace of life.</hi> But if ſo be that it ſhall pleaſe God <hi>(as one of his ſheepe)</hi> to call her vnto him,<note place="margin">Ioh. 10.27.</note> and to leade her vnto eternall life ſome while before vs; we ought willingly for Gods ſake, to bee bereaued of that comfortable delight, which this Lambe did bring vnto vs,<note place="margin">Ioh. 10.14.</note> knowing that ſhe is gone to that good Shepheard, to whom we were bound in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſdome to direct her.</p>
            <p>We are alſo bound in duty to loue her, as a kinde mother her onely daughter, whoſe affection is ſo exceeding, that God makes it a queſtion, whether it be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible <hi>that a woman can forget her childe?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſ. 49.15.</note> It is really her owne fleſh and blood. And notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, (though ſhee dearely
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:5271:101"/>loue it) if ſome good match bee offered, though it were in a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine Country, howſoeuer out of a motherly affection ſhe may ſeeke ſome delay, and <hi>deſire that the damſell may remaine with her yet ſome tenne dayes,</hi> yet after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture conſideration, the anſwere is commonly,<note place="margin">Gen. 24.50.55.</note> 
               <hi>this thing commeth from the Lord, take her and goe.</hi> For ſhe ſuppoſeth that ſhee ſhall beſtowe her on a good husband. If ſo bee then that a weake wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, can let her liuing daughter (that yet is and remaines fleſh of her fleſh) depart from her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhee is deſired of ſome earthly Bridegroome, with more reaſon ought a man of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit willingly to forgoe his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed wife, (that now is no more called his fleſh) when her heauenly Bridegroome hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:5271:102"/>her vnto him.</p>
            <p>Let vs then leaue off mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and beare our ſolitarineſſe patiently. Which if it ſeeme hard vnto vs, and that <hi>we loue our wife as our ſelfe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5.33.</note> then muſt it bee more acceptable vnto vs, that this eſtate of widdowhood, is of the twaine rather befalne vs (who by nature are the ſtronger, and may ſeeke more paſtime abroad, then if the ſaid conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on had lighted on our wife, on whom it would lye more heauy, becauſe that decencie conſtraines her to ſit lamenting within dores.</p>
            <p>But be it man or woman, Let euery one in this eſtate ſay with <hi>Iob, God hath giuen, and God hath taken,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 1.21.</note> 
               <hi>bleſſed bee the name of the Lord.</hi> Truſting that wee ſhall finde the comfort that we miſſe
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:5271:102"/>of our bed-fellow in GOD who hath taken him, or her from vs.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">5 <hi>Occaſion.</hi>
               </note> Beſides my loue (may a wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow ſay) I complaine of want: For I with my children cannot be without the helpe of my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed husband. This indeede is a bitter ſorrowe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God himſelfe ſeemes to haue compaſſion on her, who commends her diuers times vnto vs in his word. Yet not that then he firſt begins to take care of her, for it is he alone that hath maintained her, and her husband, throughout the whole courſe of their liues. And her husbands death hath not ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his mercy,<note place="margin">Pſal. 118.1. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>36.1.</note> 
               <hi>for it endures for euer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, it may be hee thus will demonſtrate vnto vs, that hee <hi>is
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:5271:103"/>curſed that truſteth in man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 17.5.</note> by this meanes to draw our hearts wholly to himſelfe. This wee learne in <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> when hee was forſaken, yea baniſht from all his kindred and friends: for then, euen then came he to be exalted and prouided for abundantly with all things. And how chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced this? The holy Scripture diuers times repeates the reaſon. <hi>For the Lord was with Ioſeph,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 39.2.21.</note> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it. Let then the ſorrowfull widdowes ſo behaue themſelues, as thoſe that truſt, and ſurely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that God is with them, and they ſhall by diuers ſignes really perceiue Gods care ouer both themſelues and their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.10.</note> 
               <hi>for they that ſeeke the Lord, ſhall not want any good thing,</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though the earthly father
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:5271:103"/>of her children be dead, their <hi>heauenly Father liues yet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12.9.</note> who hath called himſelfe.<note place="margin">Pſal. 68.6.</note> 
               <hi>A Father of the fatherleſſe, and a Iudge of the Widdowes cauſe.</hi> And did not hee prouide for that poore widdow of <hi>Sarepta,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Reg. 17.14.</note> abundance of ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, euen when the richer ſort were feeling witneſſes of ſcarſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie? Did not he marrie a poore <hi>Ruth</hi> vnto a rich &amp; famous <hi>Boos,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ruth. 4.10.</note> and a wiſe <hi>Abigail</hi> to King <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 25.41.</note> To what end hath the holy Ghoſt left vs theſe, and the like examples in holy writ? Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, for to teach all ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Widdowes and Orphanes, that God can want no meanes to aſſiſt them, and that they might (laying their mourning aſide) wholly and ſtedfaſtly comfort themſelues in his fatherly and prouident care. <hi>Truſt in GOD</hi>
               <pb n="188" facs="tcp:5271:104"/>(ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi>) <hi>and hee will bring it to paſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 39.5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, ſome man may finde himſelfe troubled in conſcience,<note place="margin">6 <hi>Occaſion.</hi>
               </note> by occaſion of the death of ſome party, becauſe hee hath not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled himſelfe with him. This indeede is a pittifull and a heauy burthen, in that therein we haue to deale with God, for neglecting that which hee ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly commandeth. And yet is it not ſo heauie, but that it may be lightned.</p>
            <p>For though we had confeſſed our fault to the deceaſed; the moſt that we could haue obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from him was, that he had forgiuen vs our offence with all his heart. Now this indeede had beene good for himſelfe: <hi>For by forgiuing vs, he ſhould haue receiued forgiueneſſe of his heauenly
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:5271:104"/>Father.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 6.14.</note> But doe we thinke hee could abſolutely haue forgiuen vs? No: it is GOD himſelfe onely that can remit vnto vs all our tranſgreſſions, <hi>I, euen I,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſ. 43.25.</note> 
               <hi>am he that blotteth out all your tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions</hi> (ſaith he by <hi>Iſaiah</hi>) and to ſeeke to him it is neuer too late. Wee doe not reade that <hi>Dauid</hi> made any moane, becauſe hee had neglected to reconcile him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vnto <hi>Vrias,</hi> though it is like he did that too; but the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall thing he minded, was to call vpon God; <hi>Waſh me, cleanſe me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.</note> 
               <hi>againſt thee onely haue I ſinned.</hi> Let vs then confeſſe our ſinnes vnto him, and entreate forgiueneſſe, and be reconciled vnto him, and ſo take away the occaſion of this our heauineſſe.</p>
            <p>But we may yet come nearer home, and make ſatisfaction to
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:5271:105"/>his heires, for that wherein wee haue offended the deceaſed. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, if wee haue offended our deceaſed Parents, in words, or deedes, wee haue a remedie at hand, to wit, that (after the afore-ſaid reconciliation made with God) we doe good to their children. That is, that wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue our ſelues ſo religiouſly, that our Parents may haue brought foorth in this world heires of the Kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. And this is it, that would not onely pleaſe God, and our Parents beſt (if yet they were aliue) but that which is alſo moſt profitable for our ſelues. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with alſo we end.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Common comforts.</note> Yet ere we leaue, wee would entreat euery one in generall, that (though it ſeeme harſh vnto them, to be without the louely
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:5271:105"/>fellowſhip of their friends) they would willingly ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to Gods will and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. Wee muſt ſay with <hi>Ely, It is the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 3.18.</note> 
               <hi>let him doe what pleaſes him.</hi> And if wee will be his ſeruants, whatſoeuer hee doeth, wee muſt like. Againe, we muſt neither expect nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to haue all things heere on earth, according to our owne minde. If this ſhould be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto vs, theſe earthly things would cauſe vs to neglect the heauenly. Our heauenly Father warnes vs by aduerſity, that wee ſhould not faſten our mindes on earthly matters. If hee did not viſite vs in this manner, wee ſhould (it may bee) grow un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindfull of him, who ought to be alone, and alwayes our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, delight, and refuge.</p>
            <pb n="192" facs="tcp:5271:106"/>
            <p>Let vs then no longer lye weltring in ſorrow, leſt by ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long lamenting wee encreaſe Gods wrath, and prouoke him to correct vs with a heauier croſſe. If a Father ſhould ſend one of his children into a farre Country, to ſee, and learne faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the childes brother in the meane while, ſhould neuer linne complaining, that hee had loſt his play-fellow; would not this continuall whining at the laſt out-weary the Father? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when his words could not herein preuaile with him, hee would at the laſt better inſtruct him with a rod, and ſo make him to be quiet. Therefore let vs alſo willingly yeeld our necks vnto the yoake of Gods will, and <hi>in patience poſſeſſe our ſoules,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk 21.19.</note> that our impatience draw not his
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:5271:106"/>wrath downe vpon vs.</p>
            <p>Wee muſt not (like children) ſtill cry and whine, nor thinke that our loue due to the dead, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires it of vs. They themſelues would chide vs, if our of heauen they ſhould behold our endleſſe lamenting for them. True loue ſhould giue vs occaſion of ioy: <hi>If ye loued me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 14.28.</note> 
               <hi>ye would reioyce</hi> (ſaith Wiſdome it ſelfe) <hi>becauſe I ſaid, I goe vnto the Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We muſt then banniſh our of our hearts by a manly, or rather a Chriſtian courage this diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and manifeſt our ſtrength by our patience. For as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayes, <hi>Hee that ruleth his Spirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 16.32.</note> 
               <hi>is better then he that taketh a Citie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The holy Scipture that ſayes, <hi>Let the dead bury the dead;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 8.22.</note> whoſe buriall yet notwithſtanding was neceſſary, with more reaſon
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:5271:107"/>ought to perſwade vs, that wee ſhould let the dead bewaile the dead, which is not neceſſary at al.</p>
            <p>But why doe we ſtill let our thoughts dwell in the graue, whither we haue willingly cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the bodies of our beſt friends to be caried, and there to be left? Let vs lift our heads higher. Let vs erect our hearts toward hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, whither God hath directed their ſoules. There the beſt part of them is yet liuing. There their ſoules remaine by the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, whereof their bodies did here delight vs. There (I ſay) our friends yet liue, This wee may learne of <hi>Iob,</hi> to whom God afterwards (as the holy Scripture witneſſeth) gaue twice as much as hee had before: To wit, <hi>for ſeauen thouſand,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 1.2. Iob 42.12.</note> 
               <hi>hee gaue him foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene thouſand ſheepe,</hi> and ſo forth.
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:5271:107"/>But in ſtead of tenne children, he gaue him but tenne againe. How then were they doubled? his liueleſſe Cattell were ſtone dead. His deceaſed children were aliue ſtill in heauen; and the ten more giuen him here, made them vp twenty. Let vs then obſerue hence, that although our louing parents, husbands, wiues, and children, or friends, are depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of this world, yet for all that, they be not therefore dead, but aliue, yea that they may ſtill be called ours. And what greater comfort or reaſon then can wee haue, to ſtay or ſtop our mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, then this?</p>
            <p>Or if we cannot haile our ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes out of the graue, let vs at leaſt behold and conſider their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies there, with the eyes of the true Apoſtolique faith, and wee
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:5271:108"/>ſhall finde them there, conſtantly expecting <hi>the reſurrection of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sym. Apoſt.</note> 
               <hi>and life euerlaſting.</hi> And this is that, which the Apoſtle on good ground charges vs,<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 4.18.</note> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort one another withall.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Calling on God.</note> And to conclude, though wee haue ſet downe much comfort, and diuers remedies againſt ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, yet <hi>except the Lord build the houſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 127.1.</note> 
               <hi>they labour in vaine that build it.</hi> In vaine doe we take in hand to cure the body: In vaine doe we inſtruct the ſpirit, vnleſſe God ſtretch forth his ayding hand. All ſorrowfull hearts muſt then fall downe before him, in whom <hi>is the fulneſſe of ioy:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 16.11.</note> and call vpon him continually to releaſe them of their ſorrow. Hee can ſoone ſcatter (through the light of his ſpirit) all thoſe thick clouds of miſery, which (often euen
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:5271:108"/>againſt our owne will) doe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe vs about. Let vs take heed onely that, with <hi>Martha,</hi> wee be not too much troubled,<note place="margin">Luk. 10.39.</note> and let vs with <hi>Mary</hi> rather, <hi>ſet our ſelues at his feete,</hi> and willingly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace his comforts.</p>
            <p>Or if we cannot wholy keepe our ſelues from ſorrowing, let vs not weepe ouer the dead, but <hi>(with the daughters of Ieruſalem) weepe for our ſelues</hi> that yet liue.<note place="margin">Luk. 23.28.</note> Let vs freely mourne for our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſins, that brought death into the world, and ſtriue to diminiſh them daily more &amp; more by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance: ſo ſhall this religious ſorrow be comfortable vnto vs, and procure vs an eternall ioy: Which we entreat that Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to grant vnto vs,<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.16.</note> which our Sauiour promiſed to ſend his Diſciples. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="198" facs="tcp:5271:109"/>
            <head>A Prayer for the ſicke, written by Mr. <hi>I. KING,</hi> Miniſter of Gods word, in London.</head>
            <p>ETernall and omnipotent God, moſt kinde and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Father, I thy poore creature, duſt &amp; aſhes, appeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy high &amp; diuine Maieſty, with a hearty confeſſion of my vileneſſe, and manifold ſinnes, wherewith in ſoule and body I am defiled, and ſo wounded, that from the ſole of my feere, to the top of my head, there is nothing ſound in me: For in my vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is nothing but blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in my will nothing but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacie againſt thy commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: my heart is a root of all iniquity, my externall mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are weapons of vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:5271:109"/>yea through my diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience incredulity, &amp; ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, I haue ſo farre turned aſide from thee, and ſtrayed from thy wayes, that I am become a ſlaue to ſinne, and a childe of wrath; whereby I haue deſerued, not only temporall puniſhments, but euen eternall death and damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if ſo be thou ſhouldeſt enter into iuſt iudgement with me. But ſeeing that thou, O Father, of all comfort, doeſt not reiect thoſe that come vnto thee, with true repentance of their manifold ſins: but haſt promiſed to heare thoſe that call on thee with a broken heart and a deiected ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: I now come vnto thee in confidence of thy bottomleſſe mercy, which thou haſt ſhowne, and offered vnto me in thy wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloued Son my Sauiour Ieſus
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:5271:110"/>Chriſt, whom thou haſt ſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to to this world, to bee a ranſome for all my ſinnes. And entreate thee O faithfull God and Father, that thou mercifully wilt heare my prayer, which I offer vnto thee in his name, (being now vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited with a heauy ſickneſſe.) Grant that I, through this thy fatherly chaſtiſing, may ſo feele the greatneſſe of my ſinnes, and heauineſſe of the ſame, that yet thereby I may not fall into de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire; But that rather through this thy fatherly correction, I may be moued to flie vnto thee, with whom is much forgiuenes, that doeſt not deſire the death of a finner, but that he repent and liue. Thou, that ſtrikeſt and woundeſt indeede as a ſeuere Iudge, with the ſword of thy law; but againe as a ſpirituall
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:5271:110"/>Chirurgion, bindeſt vp, and healeſt with the wholeſome oyle of thy holy Goſpell, that bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt indeede thy children to the vttermoſt extremity, as if it were to the torments of hell, but bringeſt them out againe: Caſt all my ſinnes behinde thy backe, Drowne them in the depth of the Sea, neuer to remember them againe. Nayle them on the Croſſe of thy Sonne my Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, waſh them in his blood: Couer them with his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that they neuer may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in account before thee. Grant me alſo that fauour, that I hartily may forgiue my neig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, that I may by a true loue, witneſſe that I am a true Diſciple of Chriſt, and borne of GOD. Let me feele, O mercifull God and Father, that this my weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:5271:111"/>is no ſigne of thy wrath, my ſinnes, but rather a teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of thy mercy, that thou cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recteſt me as a Father, that I may not run into perdition with the wicked world. Moderate, O Lord, my paines, and mercifully releaſe me out of the ſame, that I may haue freſh matter to praiſe and giue thankes to thy holy name, and to walke before thee, in vprightneſſe of heart, in true holineſſe and righteouſneſſe all the dayes of my life. Grant that my life may be nothing elſe, but a mortification of the olde man, and viuification of the new, that I dayly conſidering, that man borne of a woman, hath but a ſhort time to liue, and beſides is full of ſorrow, that his life is but a ſhaddowe, and his dayes bee vanity, that he fades away as a
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:5271:111"/>flower in the field, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not at any ſtay, may with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw my heart and cogitations from the vanity of this world. Grant, O Lord, that I may num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber my dayes, that I may apply my heart vnto wiſedome, that I may mortifie the luſt and euill concupiſcences of the fleſh, and may by little and little bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed, and become conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the image of thy Sonne. Separate, O Lord, my ſinnes from mee, before they ſeparate me from thee. Grant that this my life may be nothing elſe but a longing for my Sauiour, that I beholding him with the eyes of faith, may ſay with the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Simeon, Now letteſt thou thy ſeruant depart in peace, for mine eyes haue ſeene thy ſaluation.</hi> Yet if it be thy good will, to try me any
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:5271:112"/>longer with this thy fatherly rod: grant that I may ſubmit my ſelfe, in all obedience vnto thy holy will, being confident, that thou that art faithfull in thy mercifull promiſes, wilt lay no more on me, then thou knoweſt that my weakeneſſe is able to beare. But if it be thy fatherly will, to call me away out of this troubleſome life: Grant mee grace to be willing, and ready to forſake this earthly Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle; worke in mee a true faith, whereby I being faſtned vnto Chriſt my head, as one of his members, I may be aſſured that as I am partaker of his perſon, being fleſh of his fleſh, and bone of his bone, ſo ſhall I alſo bee partaker of all his benefits: ſo that I may ſay with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul, Chriſt hath loued me, and hath giuen him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:5271:112"/>for me.</hi> Arme me alſo with the ſame faith, as with a ſtrong ſhield againſt all temptations, that I may couragiouſly fight againſt the world, my own fleſh, yea againſt the deuill himſelfe, being aſſured, <hi>that there is no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation to them that are in Chriſt.</hi> And that neither death nor life, nor Angels, nor principalities, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, <hi>nor any creature ſhall be able to ſeperate me from the loue of GOD in Ieſus Chriſt my Lord,</hi> O mercifull God, in whoſe hand is life and death, aſſiſt me conſtantly in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict. Though the fleſh be weake, and could be content to ſay, <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther if it be poſsible let this cup paſſe away from me;</hi> Yet let the Spirit be willing and ſay, <hi>not my will, but thy will be done</hi> Helpe mee to
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:5271:113"/>conquer the terrours and panges of death, which through Chriſt is become vnto me a paſſage to eternall life: ſay vnto my ſoule, <hi>I am thy ſaluation,</hi> ſtrengthen mee in the ſtedfaſt hope of the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous reſurrection, wherein my humbled body ſhall bee made like vnto the glorified body of Chriſt. Turne my paines and anguiſh into that eternall ioy, that ſhall be in the bleſſed viſion of thy face: receiue my ſoule vnto thee, remoue her out of this vale of miſery, to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of holy Angels, and to the congregation of thy Elect. <hi>Come Lord Ieſu, come quickly.</hi> All theſe neceſſaries that I ſtand in neede of, I begge and entreate of thee O moſt mercifull God and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in the name of my onely Sauiour, concluding my petition
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:5271:113"/>with that abſolute prayer that Ieſus Chriſt himſelf hath taught his Diſciples, and all the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſaying, <hi>Our Father which art in heauen, hallowed be thy name, thy Kingdome come, thy will be done on earth as it is in heauen, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
